<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Blog of Lynn Root</title>
    <subtitle>Homepage and blog of Lynn Root. Coder, writer, speaker, and PyLady of San Francisco.</subtitle>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/" />
    <link rel="self" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/feed.xml" type="application/atom+xml" />
    <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/</id>
    <updated>2013-09-17T17:23:36Z</updated>

    <author>
        <name>Lynn Root</name>
        <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
    </author>

    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Hanging my Red Hat for headphones</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/joining-spotify/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/joining-spotify/</id>
            <updated>2013-09-17T17:21:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At the end of the month, I’ll be trading in my Red Hat for a pair of head phones: I’ll be joining &lt;a href=&#34;http://open.spotify.com/user/econchick&#34;&gt;Spotify&lt;/a&gt; in San Francisco as a Partner Engineer to work on third-party integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a fantastic experience working on &lt;a href=&#34;http://freeipa.org&#34;&gt;freeIPA&lt;/a&gt;, but found the opportunity at Spotify too awesome to pass up.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#39;ll still see me at conferences (maybe more so!).  But perhaps more exciting is the ability to dedicate some time and effort to PyLadies, the Python community, and push Spotify to contribute more to open source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m super excited to be joining Spotify, a product that I love and a team that I&amp;#39;ve admired ever since I met them at EuroPython in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can I say? I wanted more wubwub!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Karmawho.re: Your Reddit Comment Karma Visualized</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/karmawhore/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/karmawhore/</id>
            <updated>2013-09-02T02:42:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Is a lot of your time wasted from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Derping&#34;&gt;derping&lt;/a&gt; around on &lt;a href=&#34;http://reddit.com&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt;?  Do you find that you have to correct someone when they’re &lt;a href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/386/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;wrong&lt;/strong&gt; on the internet&lt;/a&gt;?  Wish that your collected comment karma was worth something?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I can’t trade you anything for your karma.  But I can provide you with awesome &lt;a href=&#34;http://d3js.org&#34;&gt;d3&lt;/a&gt; visualizations of it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.karmawho.re&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.karmawho.re&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to visualize your &lt;strike&gt;wasted time&lt;/strike&gt; collected karma from comment posts.  Search via your Reddit user name, or click “I’m feeling creepy” to visualize comments of a random user.  Try plugging in a few of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.karmawhores.net/&#34;&gt;these top comment posters&lt;/a&gt; if you find that you don’t post enough on Reddit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/karmawhore-start.png&#34; style=&#34;box-shadow: 0 1px 2px rgba(0,0,0,0.5);&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/karmawhore-time.png&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/karmawhore-totalkarma.png&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/karmawhore-wordcloud.png&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/karmawhore-buckets.png&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karmawhore was a labor day weekend project using &lt;a href=&#34;http://d3js.org&#34;&gt;d3.js&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://nvd3.org/&#34;&gt;nvd3&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jasondavies/d3-cloud&#34;&gt;d3 wordcloud&lt;/a&gt; to bring you these awesome graphs.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">PRISM-as-a-Service: Not Subject to American Law</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/prism/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/prism/</id>
            <updated>2013-08-10T23:49:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the light of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PRISM_(surveillance_program)&#34;&gt;PRISM&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/investigations/us-intelligence-mining-data-from-nine-us-internet-companies-in-broad-secret-program/2013/06/06/3a0c0da8-cebf-11e2-8845-d970ccb04497_story.html&#34;&gt;whistle blowing&lt;/a&gt;, many folks, like &lt;a href=&#34;http://fredlybrand.com/2013/06/23/an-apology-to-my-european-it-team/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theregister.co.uk/2013/06/08/what_about_a_us_tech_boycott/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.computerworld.com/cloud-storage/22305/why-prism-kills-cloud&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, are questioning whether the cloud is a viable option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This write-up, originally presented at &lt;a href=&#34;http://pycon.ca&#34;&gt;PyCon Canada 2013&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/roguelynn/prism-as-a-service-not-subject-to-american-law&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;, and video coming soon) is a look at what PRISM is, how the cloud is affected, and how we can maintain privacy in the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not a lawyer, nor have I studied law in anyway.  I’m a typical American with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.archives.gov/exhibits/charters/constitution.html&#34;&gt;US Constitution&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.archives.gov/exhibits/charters/bill_of_rights_transcript.html&#34;&gt;Bill of Rights&lt;/a&gt; engrained in my soul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor have I had any experience in three-letter-government-agencies-that-are-out-to-get-you, or currently work/have worked for a company involved in PRISM (or at least not that I’m aware of).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post has no special insight nor conspiracy theories, just painting a story from publicly available research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-is-prism&#34;&gt;What is PRISM?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PRISM stands for “Planning Tool for Resource Integration, Synchronization, and Management” and is a clandestine electronic data mining program for the purpose of mass surveillance.  PRISM aims to collect metadata that passes through US servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, the collected data &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/special/politics/prism-collection-documents/&#34;&gt;includes&lt;/a&gt; email, voice &amp;amp; video chat, videos, photos, stored data, online social networking details, among others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;who-does-it-affect-and-who-is-involved&#34;&gt;Who does it affect and who is involved?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s meant to target foreign communications and not specifically or intentionally target US citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with Microsoft in September 2007, PRISM &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/special/politics/prism-collection-documents/&#34;&gt;started collecting data&lt;/a&gt;.  Other companies include Yahoo (2008), Google (2009), Facebook (2009), PalTalk (2009), YouTube (2010), Skype (2011), AOL (2011), and Apple (2012).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;how-does-it-work&#34;&gt;How does it work?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the NSA slides &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/special/politics/prism-collection-documents/&#34;&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; on Washington Post, and from the press releases from &lt;a href=&#34;http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2013/06/what.html&#34;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/zuck/posts/10100828955847631&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/apples-commitment-to-customer-privacy/&#34;&gt;Apple&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.microsoft.com/en-us/news/Press/2013/Jun13/06-06statement.aspx&#34;&gt;Microsoft&lt;/a&gt;, and others, the NSA does not have &lt;em&gt;direct&lt;/em&gt; access to these companies&amp;#39; servers.  For the collection process, the FBI issues a directive to the company, and the company responds by supplying data (or, supposedly, denies or requests more information).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FBI uses government equipment on private company property to retrieve matching information from a participating company, such as Microsoft or Yahoo and pass it without further review to the NSA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/special/politics/prism-collection-documents/&#34;&gt;Source: Washington Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NSA then &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/special/politics/prism-collection-documents/&#34;&gt;filters the data&lt;/a&gt; by type (voice, video, call records, internet records, etc.) followed by foreign versus American subject to reduce the intake of information about Americans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;timeline&#34;&gt;Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h4 id=&#34;mass-surveillance-nothing-new-and-not-just-us&#34;&gt;Mass Surveillance: Nothing New, and not just US&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;script async class=&#34;speakerdeck-embed&#34; data-id=&#34;e8a985f0e3730130e8c53a22532026d5&#34; data-ratio=&#34;1.33333333333333&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eff.org/nsa-spying/timeline&#34;&gt;Timeline sources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unanswered-questions&#34;&gt;Unanswered Questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of detail in both the involved companies&amp;#39; statements and in the NSA slides and responses themselves leave a lot of questions.  For instance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is a target’s “foreignness” determined?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How exactly are they identifying non-US citizens?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are foreign-born US residents included as foreigners?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What if a US citizen and a foreigner communicate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What about US citizens abroad, or US citizens using services abroad?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5860003&#34;&gt;Does the NSA/FBI have jurisdiction on foreign persons/companies using services from US-based companies that are located/incorporated abroad&lt;/a&gt;?  How does physical location of the person/company/service/hardware matter? If a &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5860038&#34;&gt;company like Twitter says no&lt;/a&gt; to a request, can the NSA go to their PRISM-compliant hosts to get the desired information?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What exactly do works like “backdoor”, “direct access”, and “intentional” mean?  Do participating companies not know they are participating, therefore unaware of a “backdoor”? Or are companies knowingly allow access to their servers?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the NSA is not intentionally targeting Americans, what do they do with the accidently-collected data? or the data received from Five Eyes that includes Americans?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is the PRISM-collected data handled by the NSA? Does the NSA maintain rigorous security measures to protect against threats?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What exactly is the NSA doing with the data?  Are they merely collecting, or analyzing it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;effects-on-the-cloud&#34;&gt;Effects on the cloud&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US cloud has started to feel the pain in the wake of PRISM being outed. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloudsecurityalliance.org/&#34;&gt;Cloud Security Alliance&lt;/a&gt; conducted a &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloudsecurityalliance.org/research/surveys/#_nsa_prism&#34;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt; showing that 56% of foreign-based members are less likely to use US-based cloud providers, while 10% have all-out cancelled their contracts with US providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Governments themselves are starting to act: Germany has also &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.heise.de/newsticker/meldung/PRISM-Datenschuetzer-stoppen-neue-Datentransfers-von-Firmen-in-die-USA-1922987.html&#34;&gt;banned&lt;/a&gt; (in German) all future transfer of data to non-EU-based clouds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itif.org/&#34;&gt;Information Technology &amp;amp; Innovation Foundation&lt;/a&gt; released a report quantifying &lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.itif.org/2013-cloud-computing-costs.pdf&#34;&gt;how much PRISM will cost the US computing industry&lt;/a&gt; (PDF):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. cloud computing industry stands to lose $22 to $35 billion over the next three years as a result of the recent revelations about the NSA’s electronic surveillance programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Folks have &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theregister.co.uk/2013/06/08/what_about_a_us_tech_boycott/&#34;&gt;boycotted&lt;/a&gt; US cloud, others are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/r/worldnews/comments/1fxg0d/nsa_prism_why_im_boycotting_us_cloud_tech_and_you/caespwn&#34;&gt;experiencing&lt;/a&gt; a run on their own cloud services, and some are even &lt;a href=&#34;http://fredlybrand.com/2013/06/23/an-apology-to-my-european-it-team/&#34;&gt;apologizing&lt;/a&gt; to foreign co-workers on using US-based cloud services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-can-we-do&#34;&gt;What can we do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s difficult to defend oneself against an attacker whose capabilities you do not know.  We should approach protecting our privacy by asking some questions, defining threat scenarios, and building defenses around that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;limit-government-exposure&#34;&gt;Limit government exposure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are, in general, three reasons a government may spy: industrial espionage, political reasons, and terrorism&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By bringing cloud services within your company&amp;#39;s national jurisdiction, you effectively eliminate industrial espionage by a foreign government.  It is very unlikely to be spied on for industrial espionage by your own government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, it’s still unclear if the USA, UK, Europe, etc, can have access to data even if you host services within your own country.  However, that starts to require political solutions rather than technical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, we have no idea what the technical capabilities of these “attackers” are.  Random hackers usually do not have scale like governments do.  We have to assume government spies can do anything, but then protection costs skyrocket.  In general, though, a company’s data is not that important to governments.  It’s personal profiles that is a bit part of any kind of PRISM-like scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;diy-cloud&#34;&gt;DIY Cloud&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solutions are simply moving your business elsewhere to your own jurisdiction.  I can’t answer whether using US company’s services abroad, like &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.heroku.com/archives/2013/4/24/europe-region&#34;&gt;Heroku’s european servers&lt;/a&gt;, will or will not protect you against the US government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being that hardware is getting a lot cheaper, do-it-yourself clouds like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openstack.org/&#34;&gt;OpenStack&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.openshift.com/&#34;&gt;OpenShift&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://owncloud.org/&#34;&gt;ownCloud&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cloudstack.apache.org/&#34;&gt;CloudStack&lt;/a&gt;, etc., will give you total knowledge of what is on your machines and total control of your response if and when a hacker (government or not) gets in.  I have my own personal cloud thanks to the raspberry pi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, though, a company’s data is not that important to governments.  It’s personal profiles that is a bit part of any kind of PRISM-like scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;as-nerds-ourselves&#34;&gt;As nerds ourselves&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the question is: what level of granularity are you okay with that your government knows?  Or coming from a different direction, is it possible to go completely anonymous?  I may sound like I’m wearing a tinfoil hat, but bare with me – this is more of a proof of concept that no, it is not possible to go completely anonymous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;location-tracking&#34;&gt;Location tracking&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would imagine most folks are okay with a government knowing &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; you are inside its nation.  But how granular are you okay with in being tracked?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s difficult to “go off the grid” entirely.  As long as you carry a phone, you’re trackable. If you live in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aclu.org/technology-and-liberty/new-law-requires-warrants-cell-phone-tracking&#34;&gt;Maine&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thetakeaway.org/2013/jul/22/new-jersey-supreme-court-warrant-required-acquire-cell-phone-location-data/&#34;&gt;New Jersey&lt;/a&gt;, you’re lucky; but in the majority of the US, a search warrant is not needed to ask your cell phone carrier for your location data.  You can certainly turn off your phone, but as soon as you turn it on, location is recorded when connecting to a cell tower or wifi connection spot. In London, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://arstechnica.com/security/2013/08/no-this-isnt-a-scene-from-minority-report-this-trash-can-is-stalking-you/&#34;&gt;UK company is building smart trash cans that track every WiFi-enabled smartphone that passes by&lt;/a&gt;. In a one-week period with just 12 cans installed, more than 4 million devices were tracked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, you could rotate through pay-as-you-go phones.  You’ll have to pay with cash, but it’s unclear if ATMs log bill numbers with account numbers.  If you do have unmarked bills, then where do you buy the phone?  What store reliably does not have security cameras? The phone has a barcode to scan when purchasing; would logs of purchases be tied to camera footage? You may ask, “would the government really care? Am I that dangerous to be tracked?” Yet in the UK for instance, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/uk/2011/mar/02/cctv-cameras-watching-surveillance&#34;&gt;your every move is already being watched&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the internet, your internet service provider (ISP) will always know your connections, and can always be intercepted.  Even if you are not using a line that is tied to your name, your location can still be identified because of the MAC address associated with your connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you write a script to change your MAC address after every connection to avoid being tracked.  There are other identifying factors: there is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TCP/IP_stack_fingerprinting&#34;&gt;OS fingerprinting&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://panopticlick.eff.org&#34;&gt;browser fingerprinting&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; clear one can avoid location tracking if connected to the internet at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;behavior-profiling&#34;&gt;Behavior profiling&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assume that you can avoid being tracked by location.  You’re still trackable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you do online creates a nice &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eff.org/issues/online-behavioral-tracking&#34;&gt;behavior profile&lt;/a&gt; on you.  When do you go online? Who do you email? What websites do you visit?  This behavior is always visible to your ISP because they need to route you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when you flip open an incognito tab with Chrome, it clearly states what information is not being hidden:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/incognito.png&#34; width=&#34;650&#34; height=&#34;550&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One popular way to increase anonymity is using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.movements.org/how-to/entry/how-to-surf-the-internet-anonymously-with-tor/&#34;&gt;Tor&lt;/a&gt; project. Note, however, simply using Tor does not encrypt all of your internet activities.  However, there are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.torproject.org/download/download.html.en#Warning&#34;&gt;certain habits&lt;/a&gt; that can be done to increase the effectiveness of Tor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tor only gives you anonymity, though. It does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; provide privacy. For instance, using Tor allows you to connect to sites without being traced back to you.  Privacy protests your data, anonymity protects you.  To protect privacy, VPN is your answer. When choosing a VPN, &lt;a href=&#34;http://torrentfreak.com/vpn-services-that-take-your-anonymity-seriously-2013-edition-130302/&#34;&gt;be sure to do your research&lt;/a&gt;.  If you are to use both Tor and VPN, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/14380693?startSlide=138&#34;&gt;be sure you know what you’re doing&lt;/a&gt;, or you may end up like &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarah_Palin_email_hack&#34;&gt;this guy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eff.org/&#34;&gt;EFF&lt;/a&gt; has a great &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eff.org/pages/tor-and-https&#34;&gt;graph&lt;/a&gt; of the potentially visible data to eavesdroppers with Tor, HTTPS, and neither or both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet the status of Tor is now questionable with the owner of “Freedom Hosting” &lt;a href=&#34;https://openwatch.net/i/200/&#34;&gt;arrested&lt;/a&gt; due to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://pastebin.com/pmGEj9bV&#34;&gt;JavaScript exploit&lt;/a&gt; deployed against a Tor-user’s browser.  Even if you were to avoid these sorts of exploits, if an individual controls a relatively large percentage of Tor nodes (I can’t find the resource, but I believe about 15% is enough), the owner can de-anonymize you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming if both your Tor connection and your browser is secure, you’re using a trusty VPN service, and not downloading exploitable files, how can you avoid being profiled? It’s still difficult to hide pure browsing activity (unless you write scripts to simulate fake activity). At this point, not much else can be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about email? PGP/GPG only encrypts the body of the email.  Therefore, who you email, any x-headers, routing information, and &lt;em&gt;subject&lt;/em&gt; of the email is not encrypted. Perhaps use an obfuscatory or minimal subject line.  If you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; don’t want folks knowing who you’re emailing, then perhaps a private, self-hosted forum is the way to communicate.  How far do you want to go?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;encryption&#34;&gt;Encryption&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And SSL? Can we trust it? The general status of SSL should be considered unclear on a technical level.  With &lt;a href=&#34;http://arstechnica.com/business/2011/09/new-javascript-hacking-tool-can-intercept-paypal-other-secure-sessions/&#34;&gt;BEAST&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cert.sd/index928f.html&#34;&gt;CRIME&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://breachattack.com&#34;&gt;BREACH&lt;/a&gt; attacks on SSL presented in three consecutive years, is SSL enough?  There may be more attacks against SSL that is not public if two dudes are able to publicly present three SSL attacks three years in a row.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming that SSL is technically secure, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://arstechnica.com/security/2010/03/govts-certificate-authorities-conspire-to-spy-on-ssl-users/&#34;&gt;government can still go to a root Certificate Authority and demand its private key to facilitate man-in-the-middle attacks&lt;/a&gt;, or the CA itself &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vasco.com/company/about_vasco/press_room/news_archive/2011/news_diginotar_reports_security_incident.aspx&#34;&gt;could be compromised&lt;/a&gt;.  One way to ensure trusted certificates are being used and avoid MITM attacks is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.owasp.org/index.php/Certificate_and_Public_Key_Pinning&#34;&gt;certificate pinning&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One concern with PRISM is that the “&lt;a href=&#34;http://news.netcraft.com/archives/2013/06/25/ssl-intercepted-today-decrypted-tomorrow.html&#34;&gt;NSA logs very high volumes of internet traffic and retains captured encrypted communication for later cryptanalysis&lt;/a&gt;”.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perfect_forward_secrecy&#34;&gt;Perfect Forward Secrecy&lt;/a&gt; is one &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.computerworld.com/encryption/22366/can-nsa-see-through-encrypted-web-pages-maybe-so&#34;&gt;defense&lt;/a&gt; against this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When PFS is used, the compromise of an SSL site&amp;#39;s private key does not necessarily reveal the secrets of past private communication; connections to SSL sites which use PFS have a per-session key which is not revealed if the long-term private key is compromised. The security of PFS depends on both parties discarding the shared secret after the transaction is complete (or after a reasonable period to allow for session resumption).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://news.netcraft.com/archives/2013/06/25/ssl-intercepted-today-decrypted-tomorrow.html&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quick note though: PFS does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; protect against MITM attacks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone with access to the server&amp;#39;s private key can, of course, perform an active man in the middle attack and impersonate the server. However, they can do that only when the communication is taking place. It is not possible to pile up a mountain of encrypted traffic and decrypt it later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://community.qualys.com/blogs/securitylabs/2013/06/25/ssl-labs-deploying-forward-secrecy&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;outlook&#34;&gt;Outlook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It essentially comes down to the questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we deal with SSL?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much can we trust it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do we need to “reboot” our encryption protocols and habits entirely?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Should we reevaluate the whole idea of the certificate authority system?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether the NSA has “direct” access to PRISM-cooperating companies’ servers or has effectively &lt;a href=&#34;https://mailman.stanford.edu/pipermail/liberationtech/2013-June/008838.html&#34;&gt;hacked cryptographic constructs&lt;/a&gt;, our privacy has been challenged.  Our data is being collected, and while it may seem trivial now, one day you may be deemed a terrorist like &lt;a href=&#34;http://gawker.com/kid-who-rapped-about-marathon-bombing-now-faces-terro-486959354&#34;&gt;this kid here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First they came for the Socialists, and I did not speak out– Because I was not a Socialist. Then they came for the Trade Unionists, and I did not speak out– Because I was not a Trade Unionist. Then they came for the Jews, and I did not speak out– Because I was not a Jew. Then they came for me– and there was no one left to speak for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Martin Niemöller&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Part 2: Apache and Kerberos for Django Authentication + Authorization</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/apache-kerberos-for-django/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/apache-kerberos-for-django/</id>
            <updated>2013-05-16T23:49:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is part 2 of a series of posts on setting up Django to use external authentication.  This post explains how to setup Apache for Django to use a corporate/internal authentication environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-do-i-apache&#34;&gt;How do I Apache?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, now that my application is done and the custom user is setup, how do I actually &lt;em&gt;hook&lt;/em&gt; this into the internal network?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apache is the &lt;span id=&#34;antibuzz&#34;&gt;anti-buzzword&lt;/span&gt; if you will, but often you don’t have a choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;configuring-apache&#34;&gt;Configuring Apache&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the host machine that will be running the Apache instance, make sure to install &lt;code&gt;mod_auth_kerb&lt;/code&gt; for Kerberos, or &lt;code&gt;mod_authnz_ldap&lt;/code&gt; for LDAP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within &lt;code&gt;/etc/httpd/conf.d/&lt;/code&gt;, create another &lt;code&gt;.conf&lt;/code&gt; file, for instance: &lt;code&gt;remote_user.conf&lt;/code&gt;. You can also have this configuration within &lt;code&gt;.htaccess&lt;/code&gt; in the desired protected directory itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Configuration for Kerberos should look similar to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# remote_user.conf or .htaccess
LoadModule auth_kerb_module modules/mod_auth_kerb.so

&amp;lt;Location /&amp;gt; 
    AuthName &amp;#34;DjangoConKerberos&amp;#34;
    AuthType Kerberos
    KrbMethodNegotiate On
    KrbMethodK5Passwd Off
    KrbServiceName HTTP/$FQDN
    KrbAuthRealms KERBEROS_DOMAIN
    Krb5KeyTab /path/to/http.keytab
    Require valid-user

    Order Deny,Allow
    Deny from all
&amp;lt;/Location&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If using LDAP + Basic auth instead of Kerberos, Apache configuration should look similar to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# remote_user.conf or .htaccess
LoadModule authnz_ldap_module modules/mod_authnz_ldap.so

&amp;lt;Location /&amp;gt; 
    AuthName &amp;#34;DjangoConLDAP&amp;#34;
    AuthType Basic
    AuthBasicProvider ldap
    AuthzLDAPAuthoritative Off
    AuthLDAPURL ldap://$LDAP_URL:389/CN=...
    AuthLDAPBindDN cn=myusername,cn=Users,...
    AuthLDAPBindPassword mypassword
    Require valid-user

    Order Deny,Allow
    Deny from all
&amp;lt;/Location&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An important part of setting up Apache for an internal Kerberized system is getting a keytab for Apache.  Most likely, you won’t have access to get the needed keytab, and will need to request one from whoever manages the corporate identity system.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it’s quite easy to spin up a test environment to see if your configuration is working correctly.  I detail how to set one up in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/setting-up-a-kerberos-test-environment&#34;&gt;part 3&lt;/a&gt; of this series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;http://modauthkerb.sourceforge.net/configure.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more detailed information on the various configuration parameters for &lt;code&gt;mod_auth_kerb&lt;/code&gt; + Apache, or &lt;a href=&#34;http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.2/mod/mod_authnz_ldap.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for LDAP + Apache configuration, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.netexpertise.eu/en/apache/authentication-against-active-directory.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for Active Directory with LDAP + Apache configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will need to setup &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/dev/howto/deployment/wsgi/&#34;&gt;wsgi configuration&lt;/a&gt; for Apache to actually serve your application.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, by some &lt;em&gt;odd&lt;/em&gt; reason, you want or can use something other than Apache, there is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/fintler/nginx-mod-auth-kerb&#34;&gt;mod_auth_kerb setup&lt;/a&gt; for nginx.  &lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; I have not used or tested nginx with Kerberos setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;does-it-negotiate-testing-setup&#34;&gt;Does it negotiate? Testing setup&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h4 id=&#34;curl&#34;&gt;cURL&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d suggest to first try with &lt;code&gt;curl&lt;/code&gt; to make sure the Apache + Kerberos setup is correct:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[vagrant@client]# kinit roguelynn
Password for roguelynn@ROOTCLOUD.COM:
[vagrant@client]# curl -I --negotiate -u : \
    https://synergizeapp.strategery.com

HTTP/1.1 401 Unauthorized
Date: Wed, 15 May 2013 09:10:18 GMT
Server: Apache/2.4.4 (Fedora)
WWW-Authenticate: Negotiate
Content-type text/html; charset=iso-8859-1

HTTP/1.1 200
Date: Wed, 15 May 2013 09:10:18 GMT
Server: Apache/2.4.4 (Fedora)
WWW-Authenticate: Negotiate sOmE_RanDom_T0k3n
...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;--negotiate&lt;/code&gt; flag flips on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SPNEGO&#34;&gt;SPNego&lt;/a&gt; for cURL, and the &lt;code&gt;-u :&lt;/code&gt; forces cURL to pick up the authenticated user’s cached ticket from &lt;code&gt;kinit&lt;/code&gt;’ing.  You can see your cached ticket with &lt;code&gt;klist&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;requests.py&#34;&gt;requests.py&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For &lt;code&gt;requests&lt;/code&gt; fans:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ kinit USERNAME
$ python
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; import requests
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; from requests_kerberos import HTTPKerberosAuth
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; r = requests.get(&amp;#34;$APACHE_PROTECTED_FQDN&amp;#34;,\
                     auth=HTTPKerberosAuth())
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; r.status_code
200
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h4 id=&#34;browser&#34;&gt;Browser&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we’ll need to configure our browser to use Negotiate/SPNego:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Safari – just “works”. Thanks, Apple.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chrome&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mac:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;open &amp;#39;Google Chrome.app&amp;#39; --args\
  --auth-server-whitelist=&amp;#34;*ROGUECLOUD.COM&amp;#34;\
  --auth-negotiate-delegate-whitelist=&amp;#34;*KERBEROS_DOMAIN&amp;#34;\
  --auth-schemes=&amp;#34;basic,digest,ntlm,negotiate&amp;#34;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Linux:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;google-chrome --enable-plugins --args\
  --auth-server-whitelist=&amp;#34;*KERBEROS_DOMAIN&amp;#34;\
  --auth-negotiate-delegate-whitelist=&amp;#34;*KERBEROS_DOMAIN&amp;#34;\
  --auth-schemes=&amp;#34;basic,digest,ntlm,negotiate&amp;#34;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Windows: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;chrome.exe --auth-server-whitelist=&amp;#34;*KERBEROS_DOMAIN&amp;#34;\
  --auth-negotiate-delegate-whitelist=&amp;#34;*ROGUECLOUD.COM&amp;#34;\
  --auth-schemes=&amp;#34;basic,digest,ntlm,negotiate&amp;#34;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Firefox&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navigate to &lt;code&gt;about:config&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search for &amp;quot;negotiate&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For &lt;code&gt;network.negotiate-auth.delegation-uris&lt;/code&gt; add &lt;code&gt;.KERBEROS_DOMAIN&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For &lt;code&gt;network.negotiate-auth.trusted-uris&lt;/code&gt; add &lt;code&gt;.KERBEROS_DOMAIN&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;IE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Internet Options &amp;gt; Tools &amp;gt; Advanced Tab&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Within Security section, select &amp;quot;Enable Integrated Windows Authentication&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Restart browser&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Authenticate yourself with &lt;code&gt;kinit USERNAME&lt;/code&gt; within the terminal.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, navigating to &lt;code&gt;$APACHE_PROTECTED_FQDN&lt;/code&gt; within browser should then just work if everything is setup appropriately. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If prompted for Kerberos username/password, then Apache configuration maybe incorrect if you did not intend that, but should still authenticate with Kerberos credentials&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;authentication-vs-authorization&#34;&gt;Authentication vs Authorization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So - I’m sure this isn’t news to anyone: there’s a difference between authentication and authorization.  First is who you are, the second is what you can do.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using RemoteUserBackend and Middleware doesn’t automatically grab what the user is authorized to do; it’s just authentication.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if needed, there are ways to hook into the user database to grab permissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;accessing-permissions&#34;&gt;Accessing Permissions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say your app needs to know if a user is defined as an admin, or staff, a part of a particular group (e.g. &amp;quot;finance&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;engineering&amp;quot;) or something else that is already defined in your external auth system.  Customizing a backend is needed to connect directly to the external user datastore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, LDAP holds users in groups, through &lt;code&gt;memberOf&lt;/code&gt; parameter or something similar.  By binding to the LDAP to find what group the user is a member of, you can then define what authorization that a user has within your own app logic.  e.g. if user is a member of “admins”, then create_superuser(user).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pythonhosted.org/django-auth-ldap&#34;&gt;django-auth-ldap&lt;/a&gt; and/or &lt;a href=&#34;https://code.google.com/p/django-ldap-groups&#34;&gt;django-ldap-groups&lt;/a&gt; can be dropped into your Django app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Or one of these snippets (they are focused on Active Directory but so long as the configuration variables within your &lt;code&gt;settings.py&lt;/code&gt; are correct, it should work with a standard LDAP or IPA setup):

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://djangosnippets.org/snippets/501/&#34;&gt;Active Directory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://djangosnippets.org/snippets/901/&#34;&gt;Active Directory over SSL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://djangosnippets.org/snippets/1397/&#34;&gt;Active Directory/LDAP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://djangosnippets.org/snippets/2899/&#34;&gt;Active Directory with Groups&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a Kerberized environment, one approach may to be just getting another keytab for accessing the LDAP, although that requires the service to have wide read privileges.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How I would approach it though, at least within an IPA environment (which stores its user information in an LDAP), is to capitalize on IPA’s use of &lt;a href=&#34;https://fedorahosted.org/sssd/&#34;&gt;SSSD - System Security Services Daemon&lt;/a&gt;.  You can execute local system calls, like &lt;code&gt;getent group $USERNAME&lt;/code&gt; and SSSD grabs the group the user is a member of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sensibledevelopment.com/2011/01/a-generic-wsgi-file-for-deploying-django-with-virtualenv-and-mod_wsgi/&#34;&gt;Help with generic setup with django, virtualenv, and Apache’s mod_wsgi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 0: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/explain-like-im-5-kerberos/&#34;&gt;Explain like I’m 5: Kerberos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 1: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/django-custom-user-models&#34;&gt;Django 1.5 Custom User Models&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 3: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/setting-up-a-kerberos-test-environment&#34;&gt;Setting up a Kerberos test environment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Part 1: Django 1.5 Custom User Models</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/django-custom-user-models/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/django-custom-user-models/</id>
            <updated>2013-05-16T23:49:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is part 1 of a series of posts on setting up Django to use external authentication.  This post explains how to setup Django with custom user models for corporate/internal authentication methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone has or has had a Pointy-haired boss or client, right? micromanagement, incompetence, unaware?  Maybe you’re lucky?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So your Pointy-haired boss/client needs an web application.  Perhaps it’s an internal web app that supposed to capitalize on synergy, streamline costs, leverage assets, all those other effing  &lt;span id=&#34;buzzword&#34;&gt;buzzwords&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You hope to use postgres and Django’s default auth mechanism, but no – you have to use the corporate/internal authentication system, a.k.a - &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single_sign-on&#34;&gt;single sign-on&lt;/a&gt;. We’re trying to avoid managing separate user credentials and needing to login to the required &lt;span id=&#34;buzzword&#34;&gt;mission-critical synergy&lt;/span&gt; app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to despair, my Djangonauts - you can &lt;span id=&#34;buzzword&#34;&gt;leverage&lt;/span&gt; Django’s new custom user models!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;problem-make-an-internal-web-app&#34;&gt;Problem: Make an internal Web App&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So an overview of problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;need to integrate into internal authentication like Kerberos, LDAP, Active Directory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can’t use Postgres for authentication - BUMMER&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;leverage single sign-on within your app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;crap.-what-is-this-single-sign-on-magic&#34;&gt;Crap. What is this single sign-on magic?!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter: the new custom user model introduced in &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/dev/releases/1.5/#configurable-user-model&#34;&gt;Django 1.5&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;allows for a different identifier than the basic User Model with username greater than 30 chars&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;username can be email, twitter, etc, or add those elements as requirements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;great for Kerberos/LDAP/Active Directory authentication because often the username for those identity management systems is similar to email, &lt;code&gt;username@INTERNAL_DOMAIN&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;scenario&#34;&gt;Scenario&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s create a dummy application: &lt;code&gt;./manage.py startapp synergizerApp&lt;/code&gt;.  Just for the sake of simplicity, this is just a single django project with a single app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;creating-your-custom-user-model&#34;&gt;Creating your custom user model&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While you’re hooking into a pre-defined user database that will take care of authentication, and perhaps authorization, you can still define your own custom model by inheriting from &lt;code&gt;AbstractUserBase&lt;/code&gt; with your own additions, like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# synergizerApp/models.py

from django.contrib.auth.models import AbstractBaseUser
from django.db import models


class KerbUser(AbstractBaseUser):
    username = models.CharField(max_length=254, unique=True)
    first_name = models.CharField(max_length=30, blank=True)
    last_name = models.CharField(max_length=30, blank=True)
    email = models.EmailField(blank=True)
    synergy_level = models.IntegerField()
    is_team_player = models.BooleanField(default=False)

    USERNAME_FIELD = &amp;#39;username&amp;#39;
    REQUIRED_FIELDS = [&amp;#39;email&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;synergy_level&amp;#39;]

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because you defined a custom user model – requiring a &lt;code&gt;synergy_level&lt;/code&gt; for the user – you’ll need to define a user manager to take care of creating users &amp;amp; superusers within Django.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key parts here are just defining what a user/superuser should have, and referring to the UserManager within the user model itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;from django.contrib.auth.models import (
    AbstractBaseUser, BaseUserManager)
from django.db import models

class KerbUserManager(BaseUserManager):
    def create_user(self, email, synergy_level, 
                    password=None):
        user = self.model(email=email, 
                          synergy_level=synergy_level)
        # &amp;lt;--snip--&amp;gt;
        return user

    def create_superuser(self, email, synergy_level,
                         password):
        user = self.create_user(email, synergy_level, 
                                password=password)
        user.is_team_player = True
        user.save()
        return user


class KerbUser(AbstractBaseUser):
    username = models.CharField(max_length=254, ...)

    # &amp;lt;--snip--&amp;gt;

    objects = KerbUserManager()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within your custom user model, &lt;code&gt;KerbUser&lt;/code&gt;, you will also need to define &lt;code&gt;get_full_name&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;get_short_name&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;is_active&lt;/code&gt; which defaults to &lt;code&gt;True&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a few variables should be set within &lt;code&gt;settings.py&lt;/code&gt; file to make Django a &lt;span id=&#34;buzzword&#34;&gt;team player&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# settings.py

# &amp;lt;--snip--&amp;gt;
AUTH_USER_MODEL = &amp;#39;synergizerApp.KerbUser&amp;#39;

MIDDLEWARE_CLASSES = (
    ...
    &amp;#39;django.contrib.auth.middleware.AuthenticationMiddleware&amp;#39;,
    &amp;#39;django.contrib.auth.middleware.RemoteUserMiddleware&amp;#39;,
    ...
)

AUTHENTICATION_BACKENDS = (
    &amp;#39;django.contrib.auth.backends.RemoteUserBackend&amp;#39;,
)

# &amp;lt;--snip--&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; The order of middleware is very important: the &lt;code&gt;AuthenticationMiddleware&lt;/code&gt; must precede &lt;code&gt;RemoteUserMiddleware&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If want to use &lt;code&gt;user&lt;/code&gt; from the Kerberos&amp;#39; &lt;code&gt;user@REALM&lt;/code&gt; as the username, you can simply extend &lt;code&gt;RemoteUserBackend&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# synergizerApp/krb5.py

from django.contrib.auth.backends import RemoteUserBackend

class Krb5RemoteUserBackend(RemoteUserBackend):
    def clean_username(self, username):
        # remove @REALM from username
        return username.split(&amp;#34;@&amp;#34;)[0] 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and &lt;code&gt;settings.py&lt;/code&gt; for your custom backend defined above:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# settings.py

# &amp;lt;--snip--&amp;gt;
AUTHENTICATION_BACKENDS = (
    &amp;#39;appname.krb5.Krb5RemoteUserBackend&amp;#39;,
)
# &amp;lt;--snip--&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To access the user within the models for your application, you’ll refer to the custom user model like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# synergizerApp/models.py

from django.conf import settings
from django.db import models

class Synergy(models.Model):
    money_sink = models.ForeignKey(settings.AUTH_USER_MODEL)
    # &amp;lt;--snip--&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To access within your views:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# synergizerApp/views.py

from django.contrib.auth import get_user_model

User = get_user_model()

# &amp;lt;--snip--&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-resources&#34;&gt;Other resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 0: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/explain-like-im-5-kerberos/&#34;&gt;How Kerberos Works&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 2: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/apache-kerberos-for-django&#34;&gt;Apache and Kerberos for Django Authentication + Authorization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 3: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/setting-up-a-kerberos-test-environment&#34;&gt;Setting up a Kerberos test environment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://procrastinatingdev.com/django/using-configurable-user-models-in-django-1-5/&#34;&gt;Using configurable user models in Django&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Part 3: Setting up a Kerberos test environment</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/setting-up-a-kerberos-test-environment/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/setting-up-a-kerberos-test-environment/</id>
            <updated>2013-05-16T23:49:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is part 3 of a series of posts on setting up Django to use external authentication.  This post explains how to setup your own environment to test Django authentication against Apache and Kerberos/Active Directory/LDAP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;setting-up-your-own-test-environment&#34;&gt;Setting up your own test environment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, you only care about coding and developing. I’ve made a &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/econchick/99699a6fee2eb44d13b0&#34;&gt;Vagrantfile&lt;/a&gt; that spins up two VMs: an IPA server with a Kerberos KDC, and a client within the Kerberos realm that runs Apache, both on Fedora 18.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;setup-your-kerberos-test-environment&#34;&gt;Setup your Kerberos test environment:&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;pre lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git clone\
      https://gist.github.com/econchick/99699a6fee2eb44d13b0\
      KerbTestEnvironment
$ cd KerbTestEnvironment

# for a synced folder between local and Vagrant VM
$ mkdir synergizerApp  

# to spin up both machines at the same time:
$ vagrant up

# to spin up machines individually:
$ vagrant up ipaserver
$ vagrant up client
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h4 id=&#34;using-the-test-environment&#34;&gt;Using the test environment&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use your Kerberos test environment, make sure both VMs are up and running with &lt;code&gt;vagrant status&lt;/code&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, ssh into the &lt;strong&gt;server&lt;/strong&gt; via &lt;code&gt;vagrant ssh ipaserver&lt;/code&gt; then check to see if the IPA service is up and running, and if not, start it up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[vagrant@ipaserver]$ sudo ipactl status
[vagrant@ipaserver]$ sudo ipactl start
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be sure you can &lt;code&gt;kinit&lt;/code&gt; on the server:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[vagrant@ipaserver]$ kinit admin
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, ssh into the &lt;strong&gt;client&lt;/strong&gt; via &lt;code&gt;vagrant ssh client&lt;/code&gt;, then check to see if you can &lt;code&gt;kinit&lt;/code&gt; to make sure this VM can connect to &lt;code&gt;ipaserver&lt;/code&gt;’s KDC:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[vagrant@client]$ kinit admin
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To push your app to the client VM, you can just copy your Django code to the &lt;code&gt;KerbTestEnvironment/synergizerApp/&lt;/code&gt; directory we created earlier, and it will drop into Apache’s default directory, &lt;code&gt;/var/www/&lt;/code&gt;.  You will need to configure Apache for wsgi. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then go on with the earlier described &lt;a href=&#34;#does-it-negotiate-testing-setup&#34;&gt;testing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;possible-issues&#34;&gt;Possible issues&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you receive a similar error message during &lt;code&gt;vagrant up $VM_NAME&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following SSH command responded with a non-zero exit status.&lt;br&gt;
Vagrant assumes that this means the command failed!&lt;br&gt;
/sbin/ifup p7p1 2&amp;gt; /dev/null&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;then apply &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/monvillalon/vagrant/commit/dc9830350a0f2be3bb7a4b4e9fcefaed66c6a26a&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; fix within Vagrant’s installation.  For my Mac OS X Mountain Lion + Vagrant v1.2.2 (most up-to-date at the time of this article), it was a bit tough to find the exact place where this fix should be made.  Wherever the vagrant gems are installed, find &lt;code&gt;plugins/guests/fedora/cap/configure_network.rb&lt;/code&gt; to adjust the line that contains this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre lang=&#34;ruby&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;machine.communicate.sudo(&amp;#34;/sbin/ifup p7p#{interface} 2&amp;gt;\
                          /dev/null&amp;#34;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre lang=&#34;ruby&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;machine.communicate.sudo(&amp;#34;/sbin/ifup p7p#{interface} 2&amp;gt;\ 
                          /dev/null&amp;#34;, :error_check =&amp;gt; false)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(ya ya, a pull request containing this fix, or rather an update to ifup, should be made; who has time for that…)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you get a clock skew error during &lt;code&gt;kinit&lt;/code&gt; on the &lt;code&gt;ipaserver&lt;/code&gt;, restart IPA via &lt;code&gt;sudo ipactl restart&lt;/code&gt; and make sure &lt;code&gt;ntpd&lt;/code&gt; is running with &lt;code&gt;service ntpd status&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you get a clock skew error during &lt;code&gt;kinit&lt;/code&gt; on the &lt;code&gt;client&lt;/code&gt;, you’ll need to resync NTP. Try the following (you’ll have to do the &lt;code&gt;ntpdate&lt;/code&gt; command at least twice to adjust the NTP clock to at most 300 seconds/5 minutes difference):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[vagrant@client]$ sudo killall ntpd
[vagrant@client]$ sudo ntpdate ipaserver.example.com
[vagrant@client]$ sudo ntpdate ipaserver.example.com
[vagrant@client]$ kinit admin
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.fedoraproject.org/en-US/Fedora/17/html/FreeIPA_Guide/index.html&#34;&gt;Setting up IPA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://freeipa.org/page/HowTos&#34;&gt;User-contributed How-tos for IPA&lt;/a&gt;, including working with IPA, Interoperability with other systems, and 3rd party implementations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 0: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/explain-like-im-5-kerberos/&#34;&gt;Explain like I’m 5: Kerberos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 1: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/django-custom-user-models&#34;&gt;Django 1.5 Custom User Models&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 3: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/setting-up-a-kerberos-test-environment&#34;&gt;Setting up a Kerberos test environment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Explain like I’m 5: Kerberos</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/explain-like-im-5-kerberos/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/explain-like-im-5-kerberos/</id>
            <updated>2013-04-02T23:49:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Explain like I’m 5 years old: Kerberos – what is Kerberos, and why should I care?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this topic probably can not be explained to a 5 year-old and be understood, this is my attempt at defragmenting documentation with some visual aids and digestible language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;in-a-nutshell&#34;&gt;In a nutshell&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, Kerberos comes down to just this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a protocol for authentication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;uses tickets to authenticate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoids storing passwords locally or sending them over the internet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;involves a trusted 3rd-party&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;built on symmetric-key cryptography&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a &lt;strong&gt;ticket&lt;/strong&gt; – your proof of identity encrypted with a &lt;span id=&#34;secret-key&#34;&gt;secret key&lt;/span&gt; for the particular service requested – on your local machine (creation of a ticket is described below); so long as it’s valid, you can access the requested service that is within a Kerberos realm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, this is used within corporate/internal environments. Perhaps you want to access your internal payroll site to review what little bonus your boss has given you. Rather than re-entering your user/password credentials, your ticket (cached on your system) is used to authenticate allowing for single sign-on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your ticket is refreshed when you sign on to your computer, or when you &lt;code&gt;kinit USER&lt;/code&gt; within your terminal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the trivia-loving folks, Kerberos’ name comes from &lt;a href=&#34;http://l.ynn.me/Zxcew1&#34;&gt;Greek mythology&lt;/a&gt;, the three-headed guard dog of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hades&#34;&gt;Hades&lt;/a&gt;. It’s pretty fitting since it takes a third-party (a Key Distribution Center) to authenticate between a client and a service or host machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Hades-et-Cerberus-III.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;450&#34;/&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p id=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Hades-et-Cerberus-III.jpg&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;kerberos-realm&#34;&gt;Kerberos Realm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Admins create realms – Kerberos realms – that will encompass all that is available to access.  Granted, &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; may not have access to certain services or host machines that is defined within the policy management – developers should not access anything finance related, stuff like that. But a realm defines what Kerberos manages in terms of who can access what. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your machine, the Client, lives within this realm, as well as the service or host you want to request and the Key Distribution Center, KDC (no, not the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KGB&#34;&gt;KGB&lt;/a&gt;, although I always think of that, too).  In the following example, I separate out the Authentication Server and the Ticket Granting Server, but both are within the KDC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Kerb.001.jpg&#34; width=&#34;630&#34; height=&#34;475&#34; alt=&#34;Kerberos Realm&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-keep-in-the-back-of-your-mind&#34;&gt;To keep in the back of your mind&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may want to come back up here after you read through the gritty details on how the example works. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When requesting access to a service or host, three interactions take place between you and:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Authentication Server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Ticket Granting Server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Service or host machine that you’re wanting access to. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other important points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With each interaction, you’ll receive two messages. Each message is one that you can decrypt, and one that you can not. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The service or machine you are requesting access to &lt;strong&gt;never&lt;/strong&gt; communicates directly with the KDC.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The KDC stores all of the secret keys for user machines and services in its database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Secret keys are passwords plus a salt that are hashed – the &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.mit.edu/kerberos/krb5-current/doc/admin/conf_files/kdc_conf.html#encryption-and-salt-types&#34;&gt;hash algorithm&lt;/a&gt; is chosen during implementation of the Kerberos setup. For services or host machines, there are no passwords (who would enter it). A key is actually generated by an admin during initial setup and memorized on the service/host machine. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Again&lt;/strong&gt;, these secret keys are all stored in the KDC database; &lt;a href=&#34;#in-a-nutshell&#34;&gt;recall&lt;/a&gt; the Kerberos’ reliance on symmetric-key cryptography.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The KDC itself is encrypted with a master key to add a layer of difficulty from stealing keys from the database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are Kerberos &lt;a href=&#34;http://k5wiki.kerberos.org/wiki/Pkinit_configuration&#34;&gt;configurations&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://freeipa.org&#34;&gt;implementations&lt;/a&gt; that use public-key cryptography instead of symmetrical key encryption.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An aside:&lt;/em&gt; the order of the messages and their contents discussed here does not reflect the order in which they are sent over TCP or UDP. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example below describes what happens when you request something from an internal HTTP Service – like information regarding payroll within your corporate intranet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;you-and-the-authentication-server&#34;&gt;You and the Authentication Server&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to access an HTTP Service, but first you must introduce yourself to the Authentication Server. Logging into your computer, or &lt;code&gt;kinit USERNAME&lt;/code&gt;, initiates that introduction via a plaintext request for a Ticket Granting Ticket (TGT). The plaintext message contains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your name/ID&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the name/ID of the requested service (in this case, service is the Ticket Granting Server),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your network address (may be a list of IP addresses for multiple machines, or may be null if wanting to use on any machine), and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;requested lifetime for the validity of the TGT,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and is sent to the Authentication Server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Kerb.002.jpg&#34; width=&#34;630&#34; height=&#34;475&#34; alt=&#34;Request to AS&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Authentication Server will check if you are in the KDC database. This check is only to see if you exist; no credentials are checked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Kerb.003.jpg&#34; width=&#34;630&#34; height=&#34;475&#34; alt=&#34;AS DB check&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there are no errors (e.g. user is not found), it will randomly generate a key called a &lt;span id=&#34;tgs-session-key&#34;&gt;session key&lt;/span&gt; for use between you and the Ticket Granting Server (TGS).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Authentication Server will then send two messages back to you. One message is the TGT that contains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your name/ID,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the TGS name/ID,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;timestamp,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your network address (may be a list of IP addresses for multiple machines, or may be null if wanting to use on any machine)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lifetime of the TGT (could be what you initially requested, lower if you or the TGS’s secret keys are about to expire, or another limit that was implemented during the Kerberos setup), and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;font id=&#34;tgs-session-key&#34;&gt;TGS Session Key&lt;/font&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and is encrypted with the &lt;span id=&#34;tgs-secret-key&#34;&gt;TGS Secret Key&lt;/span&gt; . The other message contains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the TGS name/ID,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;timestamp,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lifetime (same as above), and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;font id=&#34;tgs-session-key&#34;&gt;TGS Session Key&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and is encrypted with your &lt;span id=&#34;client-secret-key&#34;&gt;Client Secret Key&lt;/span&gt;.  Note that the &lt;span id=&#34;tgs-session-key&#34;&gt;TGS Session Key&lt;/span&gt; is the shared key between you and the TGS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Kerb.004.jpg&#34; width=&#34;630&#34; height=&#34;475&#34; alt=&#34;AS Response to Client&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your &lt;span id=&#34;client-secret-key&#34;&gt;Client Secret Key&lt;/span&gt; is determined by prompting you for your password, appending a salt (made up of &lt;code&gt;user@REALMNAME.COM&lt;/code&gt;) and hashing the whole thing. Now you can use it for decrypting the second message in order to obtain the &lt;span id=&#34;tgs-session-key&#34;&gt;TGS Session Key&lt;/span&gt;. If the password is incorrect, then you will not be able to decrypt the message. Please note that this is the step in which the password you enter is implicitly validated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Kerb.005.jpg&#34; width=&#34;630&#34; height=&#34;475&#34; alt=&#34;Client Decrypt Response&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can not, however, decrypt the TGT since you do not know the &lt;span id=&#34;tgs-secret-key&#34;&gt;TGS Secret Key&lt;/span&gt;. The encrypted TGT is stored within your credential cache.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;you-and-the-ticket-granting-server&#34;&gt;You and the Ticket Granting Server&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, you have the TGT that you can not read because you do not have the &lt;span id=&#34;tgs-secret-key&#34;&gt;TGS Secret Key&lt;/span&gt; to decrypt it. You do, however, have the &lt;span id=&#34;tgs-session-key&#34;&gt;TGS Session Key&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s now your turn to send two messages. You first prepare the Authenticator, encrypted with the &lt;span id=&#34;tgs-session-key&#34;&gt;TGS Session Key&lt;/span&gt;, containing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your name/ID, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;timestamp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You send an unencrypted message that contains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the requested HTTP Service name/ID you want access to, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lifetime of the Ticket for the HTTP Service, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;along with the encrypted Authenticator and TGT to the Ticket Granting Server. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Kerb.006.jpg&#34; width=&#34;630&#34; height=&#34;475&#34; alt=&#34;Client messages to TGS&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ticket Granting Server will first check the KDC database to see if the HTTP Service exists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Kerb.007.jpg&#34; width=&#34;630&#34; height=&#34;475&#34; alt=&#34;TGS DB check&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If so, the TGS decrypts the TGT with its &lt;span id=&#34;secret-key&#34;&gt;Secret Key&lt;/span&gt; . Since the now-unencrypted TGT contains the &lt;span id=&#34;tgs-session-key&#34;&gt;TGS Session Key&lt;/span&gt;, the TGS can decrypt the Authenticator you sent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Kerb.008.jpg&#34; width=&#34;630&#34; height=&#34;475&#34; alt=&#34;TGS Decrypts messages&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TGS will then do the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;compare your client ID from the Authenticator to that of the TGT &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;compare the timestamp from the Authenticator to that of the TGT (typical Kerberos-system tolerance of difference is 2 minutes, but can be configured otherwise)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;check to see if the TGT is expired (the lifetime element),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;check that the Authenticator is not already in the TGS’s cache (for avoiding replay attacks), and &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if the network address in the original request is not null, compares the source’s IP address to your network address (or within the requested list) within the TGT.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ticket Granting Server then randomly generates the &lt;span id=&#34;http-session-key&#34;&gt;HTTP Service Session Key&lt;/span&gt;, and prepares the HTTP Service ticket for you that contains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your name/ID,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTTP Service name/ID,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your network address (may be a list of IP addresses for multiple machines, or may be null if wanting to use on any machine),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;timestamp,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lifetime of the validity of the ticket, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;font id=&#34;http-session-key&#34;&gt;HTTP Service Session Key&lt;/font&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and encrypts it with the &lt;span id=&#34;http-secret-key&#34;&gt;HTTP Service Secret Key&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Kerb.009.jpg&#34; width=&#34;630&#34; height=&#34;475&#34; alt=&#34;TGS responds to Client&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the TGS sends you two messages. One is the encrypted HTTP Service Ticket; the other contains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTTP Service name/ID,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;timestamp,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lifetime of the validity of the ticket, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;font id=&#34;http-session-key&#34;&gt;HTTP Service Session Key&lt;/font&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;that is encrypted with the &lt;span id=&#34;tgs-session-key&#34;&gt;TGS Session Key&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your machine decrypts the latter message with the &lt;span id=&#34;tgs-session-key&#34;&gt;TGS Session Key&lt;/span&gt; that it cached earlier to obtain the &lt;span id=&#34;http-session-key&#34;&gt;HTTP Service Session Key&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your machine can not, however, decrypt the HTTP Service Ticket since it’s encrypted with the &lt;span id=&#34;http-secret-key&#34;&gt;HTTP Service Secret Key&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Kerb.010.jpg&#34; width=&#34;630&#34; height=&#34;475&#34; alt=&#34;Client Decrypt TGS messages&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;you-and-the-http-service&#34;&gt;You and the HTTP Service&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To now access the HTTP Service, your machine prepares another Authenticator message that contains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your name/ID,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;timestamp,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and is encrypted with the &lt;span id=&#34;http-session-key&#34;&gt;HTTP Service Session Key&lt;/span&gt;.  Your machine then sends the Authenticator and the still-encrypted HTTP Service Ticket received from the TGS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Kerb.011.jpg&#34; width=&#34;630&#34; height=&#34;475&#34; alt=&#34;Client messages HTTP Service&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HTTP Service then decrypts the Ticket with its &lt;span id=&#34;http-secret-key&#34;&gt;Secret Key&lt;/span&gt; to obtain the &lt;span id=&#34;http-session-key&#34;&gt;HTTP Service Session Key&lt;/span&gt;.  It then uses that &lt;span id=&#34;http-session-key&#34;&gt;Session Key&lt;/span&gt; to decrypt the Authenticator message you sent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Kerb.012.jpg&#34; width=&#34;630&#34; height=&#34;475&#34; alt=&#34;HTTP Decrypts messages&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to the TGS, the HTTP Server will then do the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;compares your client ID from the Authenticator to that of the Ticket,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;compares the timestamp from the Authenticator to that of the Ticket (typical Kerberos-system tolerance of difference is 2 minutes, but can be configured otherwise),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;checks to see if the Ticket is expired (the lifetime element),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;checks that the Authenticator is not already in the HTTP Server’s cache (for avoiding replay attacks), and &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if the network address in the original request is not null, compares the source’s IP address to your network address (or within the requested list) within the Ticket.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HTTP Service then sends an Authenticator message containing its ID and timestamp in order to confirm its identity to you and is encrypted with the &lt;span id=&#34;http-session-key&#34;&gt;HTTP Service Session Key&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Kerb.013.jpg&#34; width=&#34;630&#34; height=&#34;475&#34; alt=&#34;HTTP responds with Auth&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your machine reads the Authenticator message by decrypting with the cached &lt;span id=&#34;http-session-key&#34;&gt;HTTP Service Session Key&lt;/span&gt;, and knows that it has to receive a message with the HTTP Service’s ID and timestamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Kerb.014.jpg&#34; width=&#34;630&#34; height=&#34;475&#34; alt=&#34;Client Decrypt HTTP Auth&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now you have been authenticated to use the HTTP Service. Future requests use the cached HTTP Service Ticket, so long as it has not expired as defined within the lifetime attribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I will write on this later, the HTTP Service itself must be able to support Kerberos. As well, you must also have a browser that supports &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4559.txt&#34;&gt;SPNEGO/Negotiate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Kerb.015.jpg&#34; width=&#34;630&#34; height=&#34;475&#34; alt=&#34;Authed&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps re-read &lt;a href=&#34;#to-keep-in-the-back-of-your-mind&#34;&gt;the points&lt;/a&gt; previously outlined; check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.h5l.org/&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gnu.org/software/shishi/&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; current implementation, especially &lt;a href=&#34;http://freeipa.org&#34;&gt;the one on which I am paid to work&lt;/a&gt; that communicates with &lt;a href=&#34;http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb742516.aspx&#34;&gt;this popular implementation&lt;/a&gt;; or review a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kerberos.org/software/tutorial.html&#34;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://content.hccfl.edu/pollock/AUnixSec/MoronsGuideToKerberos.htm&#34;&gt;resource guide&lt;/a&gt;, the go-to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7-LjpO2nTJo&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; that was sent to me when I started learning about Kerberos, or the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4120.txt&#34;&gt;RFC itself&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above images were rendered with Keynote with icons used from &lt;a href=&#34;http://fortawesome.github.com/Font-Awesome/&#34;&gt;font awesome&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://glyphicons.com/&#34;&gt;glyphicons&lt;/a&gt;, and are available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/roguelynn/kerberos-slides/&#34;&gt;slideshare&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&#34;break&#34;&gt;&amp;#12316;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a future posts, I’ll write up how to actually setup a Kerberos realm, setting up an HTTP Service that will accept Negotiate authentication, and writing a web application that can plug into Kerberos for its authentication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update: May 16th, 2013:&lt;/strong&gt; My &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/circus&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; on setting up a web application + Apache for Kerberos, along with creating your own Kerberos test environment. &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">The New Coder: A Path to Software Engineering</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/The-New-Coder-A-path-to-Software-Engineering/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/The-New-Coder-A-path-to-Software-Engineering/</id>
            <updated>2013-03-15T17:46:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post contains all the sources and thoughts behind my PyCon 2013 talk launching &lt;a href=&#34;http://newcoder.io&#34;&gt;newcoder.io&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5hBMlTFfOJg&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/pyconslides/sink-or-swim-5-life-jackets-to-throw-to-the-new-coder-by-lynn-root&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; are available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/SoS-slide1.png&#34; width=&#34;370&#34; height=&#34;300&#34;)/&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the influx of &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackbright.com&#34;&gt;private&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackerschool.com&#34;&gt;independent&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appacademy.io&#34;&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt; for learning how to &lt;a href=&#34;http://devbootcamp.com&#34;&gt;code&lt;/a&gt; is any indication, the ever-growing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mooc-list.com/&#34;&gt;list&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massive_open_online_course&#34;&gt;moocs&lt;/a&gt;, or the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-06-14/pandora-media-raises-234-9-million-in-ipo-after-pricing-stock-above-range.html&#34;&gt;financial&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704816604576333132239509622.html&#34;&gt;smack&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://stream.wsj.com/story/facebook-ipo/SS-2-9640/&#34;&gt;face&lt;/a&gt; is a tell-tale sign: software engineering as a career is having its 15 minutes of fame. Looking at the pace of its overall growth in terms of jobs and earnings, it’s not too far from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moore&amp;#x27;s_law&#34; title=&#34;Moore&amp;#39;s law&#34;&gt;Moore&amp;#39;s Law&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the context of history, software engineering is merely just going through its industrial phase compared to other engineering fields. There’s no revolutionary way to build a bridge or a highway; we’ve perfected the assembly line; making a guitar or violin is now more of an art than a science. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/SoS-writing-classes.png&#34; width=&#34;370&#34; height=&#34;300&#34;)/&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet we’re still &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o9pEzgHorH0&#34; title=&#34;Write fewer classes&#34;&gt;arguing&lt;/a&gt; how best to &lt;a href=&#34;http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2013/2/13/moar-classes/&#34; title=&#34;Write more classes&#34;&gt;approach&lt;/a&gt; software engineering problems and rapidly &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.topazruby.com/en/latest/&#34; title=&#34;Topaz Ruby&#34;&gt;developing&lt;/a&gt; new &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rust-lang.org/&#34; title=&#34;Rust Programming Language&#34;&gt;languages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;learning-how-to-code-in-our-industrial-revolution&#34;&gt;Learning how to code in our industrial revolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A textbook and a classroom is fine for learning more established engineering fields like architecture or manufacturing, but with revolutionary pace of software development, how best should we teach its principles? A four-year degree doesn’t merely grant you “l33t” status, certainly not by &lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.100.9130&#34; title=&#34;Learning and teaching programming: A review and discussion&#34;&gt;researchers’ standards&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/SoS-10-years.png&#34; width=&#34;370&#34; height=&#34;300&#34;)/&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One predominant theme I am seeing is that gap from learning syntax to becoming a passable junior developer. You went through &lt;a href=&#34;http://learnpythonthehardway.com&#34; title=&#34;LPTHW&#34;&gt;Learn Python the Hard Way&lt;/a&gt;, uh, now what? Sure – a for-loop is easy to identify, to code when told exactly what to do, but that’s not real life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.23.924&#34; title=&#34;Constructivism in Computer Science&#34;&gt;plenty&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.92.4923&#34; title=&#34;Learning Programming by Solving Problems&#34;&gt;debate&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.96.6748&#34; title=&#34;Students learn cs in different ways. insights from an empirical study&#34;&gt;how&lt;/a&gt; to go about &lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.60.5278&#34; title=&#34;Why Complicate Things? Introducing Programming in High School Using Python&#34;&gt;learning&lt;/a&gt; how to code. One major underlying theme among what I’ve both read and experienced is the notion of &lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.96.6748&#34; title=&#34;Students learn cs in different ways. insights from an empirical study&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;concepts for granted&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; versus &lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.96.6748&#34; title=&#34;Students learn cs in different ways. insights from an empirical study&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;concepts for context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re less likely to develop an advanced understanding of what we’re trying to master, than if we’re searching for an underlying meaning, trying to integrate the newly-learned concepts into what we already know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning from lectures and textbooks only go so far. With typical formal education, one learns that certain computer science concepts exist, like how to compile and install an OS, go deeper into how compiling or installing works, or why a particular code base does not work. But it does not necessarily bridge outside of those concepts to understand its application or how the whole works together with its parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need something to create those connections outside of those isolated concepts; to build ourselves context while learning; give personal meaning while striving for understanding as a whole. We &lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.23.924&#34; title=&#34;Constructivism in Computer Science&#34;&gt;construct&lt;/a&gt; our learning rather than simply listen and regurgitate what is taught. So how can we apply that to learning how to code? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;project-based-learning&#34;&gt;Project-based learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started off blowing bubbles - I did take one course in computer science (after I graduated); I would have failed if it weren’t for my crappy little final &lt;a href=&#34;22&#34;&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; shadowing the fact that I couldn’t code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I love it – the cold, chilly, 3am night never looked better to me. But who wants to pay $2000 for a single course whose credit won’t necessarily apply towards anything. I was drowning while from being told &amp;quot;this is how we chlorinate the water&amp;quot; to &amp;quot;here are the hydrodynamic equations that your body must follow in order to swim fast&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I ditched traditional academia and I’ve been learning to code through completing projects.  It’s been a self-directed study with motivation to actually do this for a living. It&amp;#39;s paid off - within a year, I am now a software engineer at Red Hat. Granted I still choke on water every once and a while, but I took to the water myself after studying what others do, how they code, and teaching others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;learning-through-frustration&#34;&gt;Learning through frustration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve certainly belly flopped a few times.  I tend to find myself learning more through frustration than being simply told what or how to do it. It usually ends success but not without tears and wasted time. It may not be the best way to go about learning, but it certainly challenges me to push myself through the hard times; builds up my endurance for longer races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/SoS-frustration.png&#34; width=&#34;370&#34; height=&#34;300&#34;)/&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I see myself in a good position to teach what I’ve learned - I&amp;#39;m no olympic swimmer, I still have those fresh, n00b eyes when trying to understand a code base. Yet when I try to explain it to someone else, concepts do solidify – teaching others gives that personal meaning and understanding since I want to create that context that builds that cumulative learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;passing-on-the-frustration&#34;&gt;Passing on the frustration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a selfish effort to further my understanding, I am here to coach you with 5 swim lessons: I’ve written five tutorials – well, three are complete, the other two have been coded out and need tutorial language behind it. These are meant to build on each other and thread that “concepts for context” for the new guppy in the water, but also be digestible and not overwhelming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tutorials aim to pick up where introductory or outdated tutorials leave off with fun projects. You learn how to tread water by playing water polo, not by someone dictating to move your arms and legs back and forth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So each has a purpose and a set of goals, ends on how these projects are used in real life, and where to explore afterwards in case the new coder wants to learn more in depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some subtlety baked into these projects though. In particular, the language used and how topics are presented. I’ve written each tutorial with a set of side effects in mind – indirect learning – that eventually become the goals of future tutorials. So we play water polo for treading water, but it also builds endurance and strength indirectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/SoS-knowledge.png&#34; width=&#34;370&#34; height=&#34;300&#34;)/&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want guppies to learn by doing. We can&amp;#39;t read how to swim. You have to feel the water against your hands to learn how to paddle through; you must accidently snort up water to learn how to breathe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;defined-goals&#34;&gt;defined goals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the new coder dives into the tutorial, s/he will be exposed to what Pythonic means through learning how to construct proper import statements in the proper order, how to write legible docstrings and comments, the language’s keywords when exploring file I/O.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;S/he will work with third-party packages to get a soft intro to what it means to interact with a RESTful API, how to parse the data returned from that API with different data structures. Terminology of object-oriented programming are introduced when instantiating classes and methods versus calling a function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each tutorial has the same goal of developing one’s logic in approaching a problem through organization, reading others’ code, debugging, testing, and logging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried to write these in a way that addresses any “stupid” or “naive” questions by using sidebars or gently introducing new terminology. The difference between docstrings and comments may be obvious to some people, but not all – especially when just starting out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;if-youre-curious&#34;&gt;If you’re curious&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The constructive learning is exercised by using “if you&amp;#39;re curious” side-bars. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course you’re curious as a new coder! Just a bit of positive language to entice folks to read a bit more advance topics; to push their endurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As more advanced topics are introduced through these side-bars, they are not meant to pressure anyone reading through them - you can take a break to catch your breathe - but they are guided to find out more information if the new coder is wanting to dive deeper.  If a s/he skips or doesn’t understand fully, it’s fine – the tutorial can still be completed with full understanding of the goals, and the “curious” concepts will be explored again in future tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;in-action&#34;&gt;In Action&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many times, we’re given a project in school, and we wonder, “What good is this? Is this even used in real life? am I ever going to compete in the state championships?” The application of a project is the pitfall for a lot of folks. It can be discouraging to learn how to swim without a realm to show off one&amp;#39;s skills.&lt;br&gt;
I include an “in action” conclusion with how each project is used in the industry now. These are not meaningless exercises to learn data structures or how to make a graph with matplotlib. These tutorials use the learning of data structures &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; build tools that are being used in real life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;where-to-go-from-here&#34;&gt;Where to go from here&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, one main critique for new coders is “where do I go from here” after completing how-tos and guides. I made it to state champs, is that all? &lt;br&gt;
It’s extremely difficult to learn what you need to learn, yet not know what &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be learned. To not burn out our new flying fish, each tutorial ends with guidance on where to go to from the end, including how to build upon what was just coded out, and resources on the topics covered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-tutorials&#34;&gt;The tutorials&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what exactly are the tutorials? What are my lesson plans?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dataviz&#34;&gt;DataViz&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first tutorial is data visualization. While creating some graphs and plotting on Google maps, the purpose is for the new coder to understand how to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;run a Python file from the command line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;import a Python file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;take a raw file and parse its data with Python’s data structures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The side effects of working through the dataviz tutorial are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Importing Python’s standard library as well a self-written module&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installing and importing third party packages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Licensing &amp;amp; copyrights when using third-party packages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;File Input/Output, Iterators, and Generators with using Python’s keywords and built-in functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Global variables, docstrings, list comprehensions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;api&#34;&gt;API&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second one uses the techniques from the dataviz tutorial to graph data grabbed from a public API. The project is to fetch video game platform information from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.giantbomb.com/api/&#34;&gt;Giantbomb.com&lt;/a&gt;, combine that with &lt;a href=&#34;http://research.stlouisfed.org/fred2/data/CPIAUCSL.txt&#34;&gt;CPI&lt;/a&gt; data to adjust the value of the US dollar over time and generate a bar chart to show the price development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goals :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solidify how to build a simple graph in matplotlib and file I/O&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interact with a public API&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intro to REST&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parsing command line arguments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What else folks will be exposed to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python 2 versus Python 3’s print keyword/function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Validating data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;web-scraping&#34;&gt;Web scraping&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web scraping tutorial is meant to show folks are able to grab data without the use of an API.  The project builds a web scraper using &lt;a href=&#34;http://scrapy.org/&#34;&gt;Scrapy&lt;/a&gt; to scroll through &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.livingsocial.com&#34;&gt;LivingSocial&lt;/a&gt; and save local deals to Postgres. It also includes a quick how-to on cronjobs, so folks can run this script daily. So rather than getting those annoying emails, folks can query a database when they want a deal on sky diving or hot yoga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goals of this particular tutorial are to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a more solid understanding of Python classes and inheritance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python’s generators &amp;amp; iterators&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading and writing to a database&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subtle concepts folks will be exposed to are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using an ORM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Import *&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making a portable application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s great about this tutorial is that if folks have already gone through the Django tutorial, the models should be familiar, or would be a good primer for moving onto Django.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a means of inspiration and to build a bit of personal context, the project finishes with a story of how one gal was able to continually scrape the London Olympics’ website in order to grab a ticket to the gymnastics final. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scrapy.org&#34;&gt;Scrapy&lt;/a&gt; makes use of Twisted, it creates that familiar ground when moving onto the next tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;irc-bot&#34;&gt;IRC bot&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just had to make a tutorial based off of &lt;a href=&#34;http://twistedmatrix.com/trac/&#34;&gt;Twisted&lt;/a&gt;. The project is actually based off of Jessamyn Smith’s IRC bot – the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jessamynsmith/talkbackbot&#34;&gt;talkbackbot&lt;/a&gt;, where if anyone would say “That’s what she said”, the bot would reply with a notable quote from a woman (that’s what she &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; said!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose for the new coders is to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get an intro to “how the internet works”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making a portable application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;while indirectly being exposed to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Event-driven programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IRC protocol&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The antiquated means of communication that a lot of engineers use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, software engineering is more than the internet. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sudoku-game&#34;&gt;Sudoku Game&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final tutorial walks new coders through building a GUI with a Sudoku game. With the least amount of hand-holding, the tutorial walks through how to build a game board as well as how to approach programming the logic that makes Sudoku.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goals for new coders to take away are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding Python’s vast standard library&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drawing a custom GUI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Approach logic challenges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;while indirectly being exposed to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;try &amp;amp; excepts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User-driven programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“private” methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;newcoder.io&#34;&gt;newcoder.io&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So because we’re in software engineering’s industrial revolution, we need to have a revolutionary way of learning how to code. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;displayed&#34; src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/SoS-lightbulb.png&#34; width=&#34;370&#34; height=&#34;300&#34;)/&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the lifeguard and coach, I advise our Python guppies to not get discouraged.  The way we are learning to code leaves us on the edge of the pool expecting us to compete after reading a chapter on human hydrodynamics.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try out my swim lessons at &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://newcoder.io&#34;&gt;newcoder.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - give feedback, contribute, spread it around, and use it to teach others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So please - don’t drown. Swim safe!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Soft release of my New Year&#39;s project: Salarly</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/soft-release-of-my-new-years-project/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/soft-release-of-my-new-years-project/</id>
            <updated>2013-01-26T17:46:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Finally, I can actually do some show &amp;amp; tell!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US is trying to recover from the economic crises of the late decade. We&amp;#39;re still a bit high on unemployment at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/publicdata/explore?ds=z1ebjpgk2654c1_&amp;amp;met_y=unemployment_rate&amp;amp;idim=country:US&amp;amp;fdim_y=seasonality:S&amp;amp;dl=en&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;q=us%20unemployment%20rate&#34; title=&#34;Unemployment Rate via Google&#34;&gt;7.8%&lt;/a&gt;, and a bit too low with inflation below &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.usinflationcalculator.com/inflation/current-inflation-rates/&#34; title=&#34;Inflation Rate&#34;&gt;2%&lt;/a&gt;. People are &lt;em&gt;depressed&lt;/em&gt; - job hunting, competing with hundreds of other candidates for &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; job opening, only to be ousted by the second cousin of the manager, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thought you couldn&amp;#39;t be any more depressed? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I present to you &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.salar.ly&#34; title=&#34;Salar.ly&#34;&gt;Salarly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - a way for you to browse all the internationally employed workers in the United States from 2011 - 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.salar.ly/salaries?title=Financial+Engineer&amp;company=&amp;location=&#34; alt=&#34;Financial Engineer H-1B salaries&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/salarly.png&#34; height=&#34;318px&#34; width=&#34;552px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thought your salary was good? Take a look at what a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.salar.ly/salaries/?title=Financial+Analyst&amp;amp;company=&amp;amp;location=&#34; title=&#34;Salarly: Financial Analyst&#34;&gt;Financial Analyst&lt;/a&gt; can make on an H-1B visa.  Or maybe you&amp;#39;re not convinced of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.salar.ly/salaries/?title=&amp;amp;company=&amp;amp;location=Mountain+View%2C+CA&#34; title=&#34;Salarly: Mountain View&#34;&gt;wealth&lt;/a&gt; that makes Silicon Valley so popular.  Thinking of moving somewhere? How about to where all the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.salar.ly/heatmaps/?title=engineer&#34; title=&#34;Salarly: Heatmap of Engineers&#34;&gt;engineers&lt;/a&gt; are?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#39;t take my word for it, check it out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.salar.ly&#34; title=&#34;Salar.ly&#34;&gt;yourself&lt;/a&gt;. This is all public data from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.foreignlaborcert.doleta.gov/quarterlydata.cfm&#34; title=&#34;US DoL&#34;&gt;US Department of Labor&lt;/a&gt;, lightly cleaned up for awful administrative typos, rendered using &lt;a href=&#34;http://d3js.org/&#34; title=&#34;d3.js&#34;&gt;d3.js&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://tenxer.github.com/xcharts/&#34; title=&#34;xCharts&#34;&gt;xCharts&lt;/a&gt;, some async calls with jQuery, with Django under the hood, hosted on Heroku. Mind you, we haven&amp;#39;t figured out appropriate memory management - I&amp;#39;m certain it will crash/timeout after 5 people make some queries. We&amp;#39;re also not designers - don&amp;#39;t judge.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Avoid Drowning: Swim your way through a new code base</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/avoid-drowning/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/avoid-drowning/</id>
            <updated>2013-01-10T23:47:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A month or two ago, I signed up for a lightning talk for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Women-Who-Code-SF/events/93965402/&#34; title=&#34;WWC Lightning Talk Event&#34;&gt;today&amp;#39;s&lt;/a&gt; Women Who Code event. I didn&amp;#39;t submit a title - I was more, &amp;quot;sure, I could talk!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only on Tuesday did I find out I was actually on the bill to speak! Welp, here&amp;#39;s a just-in-time presentation. My slides are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/roguelynn/avoid-drowning&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; - but basically this post flows through what&amp;#39;s presented on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-experience&#34;&gt;My experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back from Brno, and having just started a new engineering position, I feel like I knew this topic well: how to swim your way through a new code base. There may be other/better advice, but this was my take away from my first three months at Red Hat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;n-diving&#34;&gt;N&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/no_diving_small.png&#34; alt=&#34;no_diving&#34;&gt;  Diving!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might feel inclined to jump into the code base. FFS you&amp;#39;re a coder! Why wouldn&amp;#39;t you want to jump in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As most lifeguards might say of pools with shallow depths: you&amp;#39;ll break your neck and drown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s take a more holistic approach - I&amp;#39;ll walk you through how I am fumbling through getting to know two (!) code bases with questions I asked myself. Mind you, not all these questions are relevant to your situation; it all depends on your code base, naturally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;t-p-down-approach&#34;&gt;T&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/droplets_small.png&#34; alt=&#34;droplet&#34;&gt;  p-down approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the purpose of this project or product?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What problems does it solve for its target audience?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are its overall strengths and weaknesses; its selling points?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What competitive projects or products are out there?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;architecture&#34;&gt;Architecture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What major components make up the code base?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do they all fit together?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do they communicate with each other?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;break-it-apart&#34;&gt;Break it apart&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What&amp;#39;s this component or chunk&amp;#39;s purpose?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What problem does it solve for this project?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strength &amp;amp; weaknesses of this chunk or component?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does it fit with another chunk(s)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lather-rinse-repet.&#34;&gt;Lather, rinse, repe&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/repeat_small.png&#34; alt=&#34;repeat&#34;&gt;t.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continue on until you drill down to the very lowest component, the lowest before you hit the code to answer your questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should be reviewing documentation and architecture diagrams &amp;amp; walk-throughs, talking to the architect of the product/project, and your team mates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;go-with-the-flow-&#34;&gt;Go with the &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/fish_small.png&#34; alt=&#34;flow&#34;&gt; flow &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/fish_small.png&#34; alt=&#34;flow&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it&amp;#39;s time to figure out the flow of the project or product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;user&#34;&gt;User&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who is the target audience? Other developers, IT professionals, non-tech folks?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is this project used?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the learning curve for the user?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sys-admin&#34;&gt;Sys Admin&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How are users set up?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is it maintained, updated, upgraded, supported, etc?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does it work with the existing systems?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;your-manager&#34;&gt;Your Manager&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the goals of the project? Future feature implementations? Direction that this product is going?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the release cycles or pressure dates?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What other teams do you need to work with? QE? Support? Other complementary/necessary projects/products?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;developer-you&#34;&gt;Developer (YOU)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you submit and fix a bug?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is the code tested?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who are the go-to people for certain aspects of the project?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ease-in-the-water39s-a-bit-cold&#34;&gt;Ease in  &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/ease_in_small.png&#34; alt=&#34;ease&#34;&gt;  the water&amp;#39;s a bit cold&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright - git pull that code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;file-hierarchy&#34;&gt;File Hierarchy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Top-down approach again: how is this project organized? What files/modules depend on what? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does the file structure match up with the architecture you saw earlier?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where is the documentation (both for developer and user/admin)? The source code/moving parts? The test suite? (Who tests the tests!?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What modules are used? Look what&amp;#39;s being used from the language&amp;#39;s standard library, the modules defined in the package itself, and third-party packages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dependencies&#34;&gt;Dependencies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the operating system requirements? Hardware reqs?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Software requirements: is there an assumption that users have the default database needed? Or other libraries already on your machine?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the build requirements for the project?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;swim-floaties-remember-those-things-around-your-arms&#34;&gt;Swim floaties (remember those things around your arms?!)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;code&gt;$ git log&lt;/code&gt;&amp;#39;  for commit logs (watch out - it could go back years). Check out git&amp;#39;s pretty print documentation for more readable output.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;code&gt;$ git blame&lt;/code&gt;&amp;#39; is, of course, a great tool. Include -L flag for to/from line numbers, and -e flag to see emails of the contributors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dev.hubspot.com/blog/bid/57694/Git-by-a-Bus&#34; title=&#34;Git By a bus&#34;&gt;git-by-a-bus&lt;/a&gt; is a great tool goes through the logs of the code and gives you html to visually see who are the biggest contributors to which parts of the library. Highly recommend.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;challenge-yourself&#34;&gt;Challenge yourself&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write up documentation that&amp;#39;s missing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix a bug &amp;amp; submit a patch. This really forces you to understand the code, how it was written, conventions of the project, and how small pieces fit together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write more tests to increase test coverage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lifesvers&#34;&gt;Lifes&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/life_preserver_small.png&#34; alt=&#34;life&#34;&gt;vers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mentors&#34;&gt;Mentors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find an internal mentor to bug about package/product questions. It may be your lead, or someone who&amp;#39;s been there for a while.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An external mentor is great to have too - perhaps you have a language question and you don&amp;#39;t want to look stupid in front of your coworkers.  It&amp;#39;s also great to get a different point of view for how the development process works elsewhere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your manager - yep, s/he is by default a mentor, whether good or bad, or absent. Learn how to manage up if you&amp;#39;re not getting what you need at first. Avoid detailed questions and ask bigger questions like &amp;quot;how is my approach in this?&amp;quot;, or &amp;quot;am I learning at an acceptable speed?&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;research&#34;&gt;Research&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I highly recommend keeping a personal/private wiki as you learn new terms, processes, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also - a bookmarking service that helps you organize your research for quick retrieval (I recommend &lt;a href=&#34;http://pinboard.in&#34; title=&#34;Pinboard&#34;&gt;Pinboard&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Old fashioned post-its, whiteboarding, paper+pen, anything. Physically writing down a piece of information (typically architecture diagrams) helped me solidify concepts better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;suggested-reading&#34;&gt;Suggested Reading&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pragprog.com/book/tpp/the-pragmatic-programmer&#34; title=&#34;The Pragmatic Programmer&#34;&gt;The Pragmatic Programmer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A language-specific cookbook (keep near your work computer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pragprog.com/book/jcdeg/new-programmer-s-survival-manual&#34; title=&#34;New Programmer&amp;#39;s Survival Manual&#34;&gt;The New Programmer&amp;#39;s Survival Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pragprog.com/book/kcdc/the-developer-s-code&#34; title=&#34;Developer&amp;#39;s Code&#34;&gt;The Developer&amp;#39;s Code: What Real Programmers Do&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;swim-safely-&#34;&gt;Swim safely! &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/scuba_small.png&#34; alt=&#34;scuba&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">My New Years Theme</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/my-new-years-theme/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/my-new-years-theme/</id>
            <updated>2012-12-31T17:45:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t do New Years&amp;#39; resolutions. But I like to take the time and reflect on the past year to declare a theme for next year. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;s-theme-be-awesome.&#34;&gt;2012&amp;#39;s theme: Be awesome.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I accomplished that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;January - March&lt;/em&gt;: led a Python study group for &lt;a href=&#34;http://meetup.com/women-who-code-sf&#34;&gt;Women Who Code&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;March&lt;/em&gt;: Attended PyCon in Santa Clara&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;March&lt;/em&gt;: Immediately submitted a talk to OSCON after being inspired at PyCon. As well as DjangoCon EU and EuroPython.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;April&lt;/em&gt;: founded the SF chapter of &lt;a href=&#34;http://meetup.com/pyladiessf&#34;&gt;PyLadies&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;May&lt;/em&gt;: made the decision to pursue programming as a career and leave finance behind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;June&lt;/em&gt;: attended my second conference and gave my first &lt;a href=&#34;http://klewel.com/conferences/djangocon-2012/index.php?talkID=43&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; at DjangoCon EU.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;July&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l2PnVKQJg0I&#34;&gt;keynoted&lt;/a&gt; my third conference! EuroPython!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;July&lt;/em&gt;: attended OSCON and gave my third talk. Also brought PyLadies to the expo hall of the conference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;September&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/from-n00b-to-engineer-in-one-year&#34;&gt;Accepted an offer&lt;/a&gt; from Red Hat as a Software Engineer!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;October&lt;/em&gt;: Started my first engineering job!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;October&lt;/em&gt;: My second keynote! PyCarolinas!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;November&lt;/em&gt;: Gave a talk at RuPy - my first not-just-Python conference. Also gave a free Django/Python workshop for women.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;October - December&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/reflection-of-my-time-in-brno&#34;&gt;Mini-bootcamp&lt;/a&gt; at Red Hat Czech in Brno.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;December&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/crap-im-speaking&#34;&gt;Made it to #4&lt;/a&gt; of Hacker News with my new static blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;December&lt;/em&gt;: Went to Zagreb, Croatia to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=450870981637921&amp;amp;set=t.14900117&amp;amp;type=3&amp;amp;theater&#34;&gt;host&lt;/a&gt; a Django + Python workshop!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The events I held and/or led for PyLadies were a lot of fun:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kickoff hackathon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git workshop x 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Django workshop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Udacity &amp;amp; Coursera study groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mini-DjangoCon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mini-PyCon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moar hackathons!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contributing to OSS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SF Django + PyLadies sprint on Django&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing PyCon proposals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as organizing the DjangoCon US scholarships for PyLadies and for the DSF and helping spread the PyLadies chapters in Atlanta, NYC, Seattle, PDX, and elsewhere. A new PyLadies website that I started should be up soon too that will include a PyLady Events Code of Conduct. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-the-theme-for-2013&#34;&gt;What is the theme for 2013?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had an epic year: met so many fantastic people in the Python world and in the San Francisco community including Python + Django core devs and community leaders; got the guts to give talks (and actually enjoy giving them!); got a job that I freaking love. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what will the theme be for 2013? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be &lt;strong&gt;awesome-&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already lined up is a bunch of talks &amp;amp; conferences: PyCon, DjangoCon EU, EuroPython, and PyCon Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have this awesome task of integrating FreeIPA -&amp;gt; OpenShift that at which I &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; freaking succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that I&amp;#39;d like to do more of is commit code to OSS projects. Currently that is the premise of my job, but I&amp;#39;d like to contribute to projects outside of those that pay me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2012 paved a great road for me to continue down. How could I not continue to be awesome?!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Reflection of my time in Brno</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/reflection-of-my-time-in-brno/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/reflection-of-my-time-in-brno/</id>
            <updated>2012-12-21T17:45:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m just returning to San Francisco from spending two months at &lt;a href=&#34;https://maps.google.com/maps?q=red+hat+czech&amp;amp;ll=49.226623,16.581266&amp;amp;spn=0.007875,0.017424&amp;amp;hq=red+hat+czech&amp;amp;t=m&amp;amp;z=16&amp;amp;iwloc=A&#34; title=&#34;Red Hat Czech&#34;&gt;Red Hat Czech&lt;/a&gt; in Brno, Czech Republic. It had its ups and downs, but most of all, I found it important and pivotal to my career as I develop into an engineer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I need to be honest: throughout 7 of the 8 weeks I spent in Brno, I felt completely and utterly lost. I struggle with the lack of guidance given, especially being brand new into engineering as a profession.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My job for the next year is to integrate freeIPA into &lt;a href=&#34;http://openshift.rhc.com&#34; title=&#34;OpenShift&#34;&gt;OpenShift&lt;/a&gt;, followed by a few more prominent OSS projects. During my one-on-one phone calls with my manager, he says, literally, &amp;quot;You need to develop a deep understanding of the freeIPA project,&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;You need to figure out what you don&amp;#39;t know, and learn it,&amp;quot; without any further guidance other than that I need to accomplish by end of February: to have a proof of concept of integration of IPA -&amp;gt; OpenShift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words: &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/no_idea_dog.png&#34; alt=&#34;no_idea_dog&#34; title=&#34;I have no idea what I&amp;#39;m doing&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;from-email-setup-to-patch-submission-in-8-days-then-what&#34;&gt;From email setup to patch submission in 8 days, then what?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I previously &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/from-email-setup-to-patch-submission-in-8-days&#34; title=&#34;From email setup to patch submission in 8 days&#34;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; about the progress I was making.  TL;DR - I submitted a patch in the first two weeks of working (mind you, it was immediately NACKed and a lesson was learned in testing).  But not much followed other than a handful of other patches. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, I learned bits of the IPA package in detail in regards to code and moving parts, and on the grand scale of how LDAP, DNS, AD trusts, Kerberos, Daemon, NTP, Certificate Authority, etc, all talk to each other and &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; it makes freeIPA appealing to sys admins, developers, etc. But it was (and still is) excruciatingly difficult to develop an understanding of what parts need to be integrated, and when I need to take step back and learn the deep, dark corners of DNS, BIND, and Apache. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank god for mentors outside of my team as well; stupid questions about the Python language, like &amp;quot;Isn&amp;#39;t it bad to have import *? Why?&amp;quot; were met with impatience at work. That&amp;#39;s not to say my team mates weren&amp;#39;t helpful; I had many ELI5 moments with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-expectations&#34;&gt;My Expectations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had this idea in my head that I would write more than ~15-20 lines of code for the IPA project. Correction: I assumed I&amp;#39;d write more &lt;em&gt;Python&lt;/em&gt; code during this time here in Brno. I wanted to learn how to write good code, the design pattern of the project, maybe write a test or two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-i-learned&#34;&gt;What I learned&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I actually ended up learning was the overall Linux file system (naturally), Vim, git, the process of submitting patches for review, public versus private errors, virtual machines (and the many ways to break them), and git blame, &lt;a href=&#34;http://andyjeffries.co.uk/articles/25-tips-for-intermediate-git-users&#34; title=&#34;Tips for intermediate git users&#34;&gt;git reset HEAD@{1 hour ago}&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tomheon/git_by_a_bus&#34; title=&#34;Git by a Bus&#34;&gt;git-by-a-bus&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other things I&amp;#39;m sure some take for granted like iptables, key-bindings &amp;amp; keyboard shortcuts (using those make me feel like a baller), vimrc, simple bash commands &amp;amp; scripting, and the like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, I also learned a bit of Ruby. To be honest, I&amp;#39;ve written more Ruby code for OpenShift than Python code for freeIPA. I&amp;#39;ve started to make a list of grievances of the Ruby language when coming from Python. #snark&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also learned the structure of OpenShift - the two Apache servers it uses, the broken installation scripts, the larger picture of what of freeIPA needs to be integrated where.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-i-need-to-learn&#34;&gt;What I need to learn&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still have a ways to go in learning to program in Ruby, but it&amp;#39;s understandably easier when I have an okay grasp on programming in Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apache is still a black hole to me, but I&amp;#39;ve begun to understand what pieces need to be added to OpenShift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have no freaking clue how &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; to integrate a project that&amp;#39;s written in Python into a Ruby-based project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also need to develop a better understanding of GSSAPI (supposedly an implementation of an API, written in Python, Ruby, whatever, that appropriately talks to Kerberos, written in C). This understanding will needed for when the DNS dynamically updates hosts (through nsupdate) and there needs to be a Kerberos-based authentication handshake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-troubles-me&#34;&gt;What troubles me&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This task I am meant to do is complex; it&amp;#39;s not an application where I can go bug my dev friends for the best library or approach. These are two different projects where the integration happens at a level that folks have experience in either but not both. &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; am the integration point; &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; am supposed to have an understanding of these two systems, how they differ and compare in setup. This requires a deep understanding of how the internet works, of Linux systems, and of security implementations, among other things that I can&amp;#39;t even conceive of right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What scares the sh!t out of me is that there is no one that knows how to do this better than me. #wat &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fear of failure has never been stronger, but it is a great motivator.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">CR@P I&#39;M SPEAKING AT [insert conference here]! How do I prepare?</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/crap-im-speaking/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/crap-im-speaking/</id>
            <updated>2012-12-03T22:52:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You just got a notice saying that your talk was accepted to [some huge freaking conference]. Awesome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh but wait, now you have to actually &lt;em&gt;talk&lt;/em&gt;. That entails preparation, and speaking in front of people!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-1-let-it-set-in.&#34;&gt;Step 1: Let it set in.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breathe. Maybe pour a glass of wine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-2-find-inspiration.&#34;&gt;Step 2: Find inspiration.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little research on how to speak well can go a long way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;reading&#34;&gt;Reading&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can suggest &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Confessions-Public-Speaker-English/dp/1449301959&#34; title=&#34;Confessions of a Public Speaker&#34;&gt;Confessions of a Public Speaker&lt;/a&gt;. The book is easily digestible and pretty humorous. The author offers great practical advice, and while it is more of a how-to book, it reads like a novel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another book I recommend is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Presentation-Zen-Simple-Design-Delivery/dp/0321525655&#34; title=&#34;Presentation Zen&#34;&gt;Presentation Zen&lt;/a&gt;. Please, if you only get one thing out of this book, it&amp;#39;s is that simplicity matters, but black font on a white background sucks.  The main point, though, is that the slides should support you, the speaker, and not detract.  It offers great advice on design tips, planning, and delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;watching&#34;&gt;Watching&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some fantastic folks that give talks.  One of my absolute favorites is a TED talk from Benjamin Zander on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/benjamin_zander_on_music_and_passion.html&#34; title=&#34;Benjamin Zander TED Talk&#34;&gt;The transformative power of classical music&lt;/a&gt;. This dude is so epic, so wrapped up in his own passion that he immediately connects with his audience. He talks about the disconnect between classical music and mainstream society today. But really, he could talk about anything and I&amp;#39;d still watch him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another one of my favorite TED talks is by Elizabeth Gilbert, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=86x-u-tz0MA&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&#34; title=&#34;Elizabeth Gilbert TED Talk&#34;&gt;Your elusive creative genius&lt;/a&gt;. She talks about everyone having a genius within. But what is remarkable is how much effort she put into practicing this talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A technical talk that I thoroughly enjoyed was Jessica McKellar&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://klewel.com/conferences/djangocon-2012/index.php?talkID=35&#34; title=&#34;Jessica McKellar Keynote at DjangoCon EU 2012&#34;&gt;Keynote&lt;/a&gt; at DjangoCon EU in 2012. She was critical in a positive way, and very engaging with the audience because of her spot-on observations about Django&amp;#39;s weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-3-write-out-your-talk.&#34;&gt;Step 3: Write out your talk.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sit down and write out your talk. Perhaps when submitting your proposal, you gave an outline. Flesh that out a bit with solid speaking points. What I typically do is type it out on a text editor, a sentence or two per point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One solid piece of advice is to follow this flow:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who am I?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why am I here?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why do you care?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beginning your talk stating who you are, why you are speaking, and what the audience&amp;#39;s take-away will allow the audience to have a good idea of what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-4-practice.&#34;&gt;Step 4: Practice.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yep, you knew that was coming. Craig Kerstiens wrote up a great &lt;a href=&#34;http://craigkerstiens.com/2012/06/19/pro-tips-for-conference-talks/&#34; title=&#34;Craig Kerstiens&amp;#39; Pro-tips for Conference Talks&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; containing tips for preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, practice at home in front of friends (perhaps entice them with a free meal, first) and/or practice locally at meetups or events like &lt;a href=&#34;http://igniteshow.com/&#34; title=&#34;Ignite&#34;&gt;Ignite&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pecha-kucha.org/&#34; title=&#34;Pecha Kucha&#34;&gt;Pecha Kucha&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is vital so you can get feedback. Perhaps your message wasn&amp;#39;t clear, or your font on your slides are too similar to comic sans. Maybe you fumble and don&amp;#39;t notice it with too many &amp;quot;um&amp;quot;s and &amp;quot;whatnot&amp;quot;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-5-relax.&#34;&gt;Step 5: Relax.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a former collegiate athlete, it was known that &amp;#39;the night before the night before&amp;#39; was the most important. For instance, if your talk is on Saturday, Thursday night&amp;#39;s sleep will affect your energy level and stamina (and thus, affecting nerves and confidence) more than Friday. That&amp;#39;s not to say rest on Thursday and party on Friday. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another tidbit from my athlete days is to ease up on yourself the day before. Relax, tune out, don&amp;#39;t stress. Assuming you have practiced your talk beforehand and are comfortable, then ease up the day before. No need to stress about getting one more practice run in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I feel like this portion of advice will fall on deaf ears seeing that a lot of folks are procrastinators like myself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck, and knock &amp;#39;em dead!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">From email setup to patch submission in 8 days.</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/from-email-setup-to-patch-submission-in-8-days/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/from-email-setup-to-patch-submission-in-8-days/</id>
            <updated>2012-11-06T17:45:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hellz yea, I&amp;#39;m a freaking engineer (sounds more hilarious in my head then it reads). Now who the hell wouldn&amp;#39;t want to be an engineer? Fellow PyLady, Julia Grace, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jewelia/status/262665853483499520&#34; title=&#34;Tweet from Julia Grace&#34;&gt;asked&lt;/a&gt; about my expectations of being an engineer versus what I actually experienced.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;tldr-it39s-awesome.&#34;&gt;TL;DR: It&amp;#39;s awesome.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s the basic run down: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;asked-advice-from-systers-amp-devchix-mailing-list&#34;&gt;Asked advice from Systers &amp;amp; DevChix Mailing List&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(exact quotes, but leaving anonymous):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Curiosity will keep you from becoming one of the &amp;#39;not my job&amp;#39; people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Remember that a lot of engineers don&amp;#39;t have the best people skills so some &amp;#39;rude&amp;#39; people are that way unintentionally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; If they dont answer questions, it is most likely because they dont know the answers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Build relationships if possible. Never miss a happy hour type of thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &amp;quot;Where did you learn that?&amp;quot; is an interesting question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Figure out the ways in which you like to work- and others like to work- first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Many guys truly don&amp;#39;t think that women can or should be coding as equals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; At least 89% of the time, by the time I have really defined my question, I have figured out the answer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;expectations-and-preformed-thoughts-amp-concerns&#34;&gt;Expectations and Preformed Thoughts &amp;amp; Concerns:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; I would have to wind down my community engagements to an &amp;#39;acceptable&amp;#39; level, e.g. only x amount of non-Red Hat related conferences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Thrown into code to fix a bug/patch/whatever&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Spend wayyyy too much time thinking over a trivial aspect of said bug/patch/whatever.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Many naive questions from me, met with a poor/mean/unadjusted attitude, or worse, lack of any sort of emotional response (I&amp;#39;d rather -know- I annoy you than wonder if you loathe my questions).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; I&amp;#39;d be restricted from doing certain things; &amp;quot;when you&amp;#39;re ready for it&amp;quot; aka &amp;quot;when I&amp;#39;m ready to give this piece of my job up and move on to something better.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;i-set-expectations-formyself-too&#34;&gt;I set expectations for &lt;em&gt;myself&lt;/em&gt; too:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Learn this shit fast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Be awesome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Make a &amp;#39;mark&amp;#39; of myself (in terms of fixing bugs, finding errors in code or optimizing, helping users of the project, etc).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Learn faster than what is thrown at me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Submit a patch by the end of the 3rd week (end of the 1st full week in Brno).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Maintain awesomeness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;how-the-first-few-weeks-actually-went&#34;&gt;How the first few weeks actually went:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Crash course on LDAP &amp;amp; Kerberos, how to create VMs both on my local machine and on remote servers (I feel dangerous now).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;My last name &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; awesome.  However, sometimes I misread my terminal prompt:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[lroot @ remote-server] $ vim /accessible/by/root.conf&lt;br&gt;
Must be root to setup this server!&lt;br&gt;
/me what? I thought I...oh damn&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Learning Linux machines like woah.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes just restarting does work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have achieved new levels of git-fu. (git rebase, squash &amp;amp; reflog are a n00b&amp;#39;s best tools)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Realized Macs are only popular for their GUIs and Aluminum casing (not giving mine up anytime soon, though)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;These folks have a lot of patience for someone just learning like me.  Very comforting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;People don&amp;#39;t need free meals/fish deliveries/spousal salaries upon death to be happy to work somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is SO freaking nice not to worry about being in the office during the same time as your manager (precious &amp;#39;face time&amp;#39;); clocking every minute of every hour that has any relation to work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Engineers are so relaxed and fun to work with. I feel no pressure, and therefore no nerves when asking questions.  Little things like, &amp;#39;here are the IRC channels we&amp;#39;re in...&amp;#39; and &amp;#39;Thursday&amp;#39;s the best because it&amp;#39;s breakfast day.&amp;#39;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;My manager flat out said &amp;quot;I won&amp;#39;t read it&amp;quot; when I forwarded him &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/2012-10-21-community-ftw-kicking-of-the-pycarolinas-community&#34; title=&#34;Community FTW&#34;&gt;my post&lt;/a&gt; about the community talk I gave at PyCarolinas (among other questions &amp;amp; discussion points). Damn that guy is awesome. No nonsense, no bs, no coddling, very helpful, thinks outside the box, and brilliant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;My manager also flat out said &amp;quot;That&amp;#39;s why we hired you&amp;quot; when I asked him about being invited to speak at conferences. hellz yea.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I can surprise a few people with the little Czech knowledge I&amp;#39;ve retained.  &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;jedno velky pivo, prosim.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was assigned 5 tickets on day #2 in Brno. This will probably be the only time I will be excited to be assigned tickets. They seem to be the types of tickets that are &amp;#39;easy pickens&amp;#39; but also give the challenge of making you dig through the whole freaking code base only to find the issue comes from an outside package. /phew &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.redhat.com/archives/freeipa-devel/2012-October/msg00556.html&#34;&gt;I SUBMITTED MY FIRST PATCH&lt;/a&gt; (day #3 in Brno. 8 days of learning terms/code/git/processes, ignoring travel days, orientation, blah). &lt;em&gt;Side note: that patch broke everything. I learned a lesson in tests the following day.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;cultural-differences&#34;&gt;Cultural Differences:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/juliaelman/status/262666318715707392%20&#34; title=&#34;Julia Elman&amp;#39;s tweet&#34;&gt;asked&lt;/a&gt; about what differences I&amp;#39;ve seen in the engineering cultures, and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/aesptux/status/262668691731263488&#34; title=&#34;Adrian Espinosa&amp;#39;s tweet&#34;&gt;moving abroad experience&lt;/a&gt; in general.  Immediately, my memory is refreshed on how hyper-sexualized women are dressed here.  I wear converse or pumas everyday -&amp;gt; flag for &amp;#39;I&amp;#39;m not from here!&amp;#39; as many women where heals (not crazy tall ones, although some do).  And hygiene can be an issue for some folks (lulz).  Also, while it&amp;#39;s still relatively cheap in Czech Rep (2006: 22-24 Kc to 1 USD, now: 20 Kc to 1 USD), cost of living has gone up. Food is more expensive, housing, Ikea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediate engineering culture differences are hard to pick up right now, and I hope to be able to have a better PoV after 2 months.  Every so often, I get a surprised look when I ask a question, giving me the impression that I&amp;#39;m not as much of a n00b as was thought.  I think that more comes from the reputation that preceded me, the discussions that were had before I arrived.  I don&amp;#39;t read into this at all.  I mean - no one told me to read into the package code before arriving... but I did, and it&amp;#39;s&lt;br&gt;
helped a lot.  I haven&amp;#39;t been approached inappropriately, scoffed at, or met with impatience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all: this &lt;em&gt;job&lt;/em&gt; lifestyle is utterly fantastic.  I got hired because I like to speak AND code AND continually learn. And I have expectations for myself to continue to speak AND code AND learn.  Look at that? all aligned! Just one drawback: I dream in test failures now.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">NetSec for n00bs, part III: Simple Intro Public Key Crypto</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/netsec-for-n00bs-part-iii-simple-intro-public-key-crypto/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/netsec-for-n00bs-part-iii-simple-intro-public-key-crypto/</id>
            <updated>2012-10-15T17:45:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is part 3 in a short intro series for netsec.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/2012-10-01-netsec-for-n00bs-part-i-password-storage&#34; title=&#34;Password Storage&#34;&gt;Part I&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/2012-10-03-netsec-for-n00bs-part-ii-ciphers-symmetric&#34; title=&#34;Symmetric Ciphers&#34;&gt;Part II&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/r/AskReddit/comments/1198on/i_fucking_love_riddles_what_are_your_best_hardest/c6kfncq&#34; title=&#34;AskReddit: Riddles&#34;&gt;Riddle time&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: You live in a country with a corrupt mail system. They open every package if they can. You put a lock on the box. You can&amp;#39;t mail a key. How does the receiving person open the box? &lt;br&gt;
A: Send the box with the lock to this person. He can&amp;#39;t open it, but he can put another lock on this box. This person sends this box with the 2 locks back to you, you unlock your lock and send it back again. So there is just his lock on the box and he can finally open it...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how public/private key crypto, aka asymmetric encryption (also: remember this riddle for technical interviews). Essentially you have two keys.  One is private, which you can imagine, only your computer knows and has access to.  The other is public, which you can give out to any sort of service that wants to talk to your computer securely. Let&amp;#39;s use GitHub for example - you are working on some code, commit locally, then finally make the decision (after you squash all your messy commits) to push to the remote repo on GitHub.  In order to do so, you need to give GitHub your public key. How do you get your public key? In your terminal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    $ ssh-keygen -t rsa -C &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:your_email@youremail.com&#34;&gt;your_email@youremail.com&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; &lt;br&gt;
    # generates a public key, saves it in ~/.ssh&lt;br&gt;
    # you will be asked for a passphrase to associate with the public key&lt;br&gt;
    $ pbcopy &amp;lt; ~/.ssh/id_rsa.pub&lt;br&gt;
    # creates a copy of the public key to your clipboard&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you pasted the key into your GitHub account (more solid directions &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/articles/generating-ssh-keys&#34; title=&#34;GitHub SSH key gen&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Now GitHub has your public key, and can communicate with your computer when you want to push code to a GitHub-hosted remote repo. When you push/pull code from the remote repo, GitHub sends a scrambled message that only your private key can decode, and vice versa, your computer sends a message encoded by your private key that can only be decoded by your public key.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If everything checks out, then the &amp;#39;transaction&amp;#39; happens - push/pull code. The algorithm to compute public/private keys is based on prime numbers and the fact that it is difficult to deduce a private key from its associated public key.  It&amp;#39;s simple to figure out the product of two prime numbers, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.see.ed.ac.uk/it/online/memos/pkey.html&#34; title=&#34;Intro to public key encryption&#34;&gt;but it is much more difficult to factor a number&lt;/a&gt; (e.g. 101 * 113 = x is far more easier to figure out than x * y = 11413). &lt;a href=&#34;http://searchsecurity.techtarget.com/definition/PKI&#34; title=&#34;What is PKI?&#34;&gt;To summarize&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To send an encrypted message, use the receiver&amp;#39;s public key&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To send an encrypted signature, use the sender&amp;#39;s private key&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To decrypt an encrypted message, use the receiver&amp;#39;s private key&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To decrypt an encrypted signature (and authenticate the sender), use the sender&amp;#39;s public key&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">NetSec for n00bs, part II: Ciphers (symmetric)</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/netsec-for-n00bs-part-ii-ciphers-symmetric/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/netsec-for-n00bs-part-ii-ciphers-symmetric/</id>
            <updated>2012-10-03T17:45:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A continuation of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/2012-10-01-netsec-for-n00bs-part-i-password-storage&#34; title=&#34;Netsec for n00bs Part I&#34;&gt;NetSec for n00bs, part I: Password Storage&lt;/a&gt; A cipher is basically an algorithm to perform encryption and decryption. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Important to note: cipher algorithms, as opposed to hash algorithms, go both ways, meaning if you process a plain text to encrypted text using a cipher, you use that same cipher to decrypt the encrypted text back to plain text, aka symmetric key encryption. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very simple, widely known example (and not at all secure) is called a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caesar_cipher&#34; title=&#34;Wiki: Caesar Cipher&#34;&gt;Caesar Cipher&lt;/a&gt;.  Let&amp;#39;s say you are in primary school, and you want to write a note to your neighbor saying &amp;#39;I think Jon is cute.&amp;#39;  But god forbid that either Jonor your teacher intercepts such a note!  Instead you are clever; for each letter in that phrase, you shift it in the alphabet by 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
    Plain :  ABCDEFGHIJKLMNOPQRSTUVWXYZ
    Cipher:  DEFGHIJKLMNOPQRSTUVWXYZABC
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your message would read as: &amp;quot;l wklqn mrq lv fxwh.&amp;quot; This would be pretty easy to break, no?  All you&amp;#39;d have to do is try each shift 25 times.  Or you can look at the ciphered text and see &amp;#39;l&amp;#39; is used three times, once alone at the start of the phrase, once in the middle of the second word, and again in the fourth.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the English language, A &amp;amp; I are the only letters that can stand by themselves.  Seeing as how we intercepted a primary school girl&amp;#39;s note, one can assume that the message would have herself as the subject of the phrase.  Assuming l = i, you have figured out the shift of the Caesar cipher, and can easily figure out the rest of the message. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding some complexity to the Caesar cipher is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vigen%C3%A8re_cipher&#34; title=&#34;wiki Vigenere cipher&#34;&gt;Vigenère cipher&lt;/a&gt;.  This one is very similar, but uses multiple Caesar ciphers based on a keyword. To expound on our example, let&amp;#39;s say our keyword will be &amp;#39;playground.&amp;#39;  We&amp;#39;d then use the (not so) &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=File:Vigen%C3%A8re_square_shading.svg&amp;amp;page=1&#34; title=&#34;Vigenere square&#34;&gt;super secret decoder ring&lt;/a&gt; that Vigenere developed to encode with the keyword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
    PLAINTEXT: ITHINKTHATJONISCUTE
    KEY WORD : PLAYGROUNDPLAYGROUN
    ENCRYPTED: XEHGTBHBNWYZNGYTINR
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The letter &amp;#39;i&amp;#39; is paired up with &amp;#39;p&amp;#39;, so you&amp;#39;d use column &amp;#39;i&amp;#39; and row &amp;#39;p&amp;#39; in the super secret decoder ring, aka the Vigenere square, to get the ciphered letter.  This way, you&amp;#39;d only have to keep the keyword secret. In symmetric key encryption, the drawback is that both parties, the sender &amp;amp; the (intended) receiver of the message, need to know what the key is, as opposed to public-key encryption (will be part III of this series). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advanced_Encryption_Standard&#34; title=&#34;Wiki: AES&#34;&gt;Advanced Encryption Standard&lt;/a&gt; (AES) is a well-respected specification for symmetric-key encryption, and became federal standard in the early 2000s and deemed suitable for &amp;#39;secret&amp;#39; and &amp;#39;top secret&amp;#39; information (with varying degrees of key length needed depending on which level of confidentiality is needed). While the algorithm is itself difficult to break (an attack on the algorithm itself &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advanced_Encryption_Standard#Known_attacks&#34; title=&#34;Wiki: AES known attacks&#34;&gt;happened around 2009&lt;/a&gt; on certain versions of AES), side-channeling is effectively attacking an implementation of AES with a longer known history of attacks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Side-channeling is quite cool and devious, if I may say.  Attackers use information that the implemented AES system gives off: timing info, power consumption, etc.   If using a timing attack, one would &amp;#39;listen&amp;#39; for how long it takes the hardware that holds the algorithm to compute cryptographic operations. Using statistical analysis, one can sometimes figure out the whole key. Alright I think that completes the part II of NetSec for n00bs.  Part III will continue on with asymmetric encryption/public key crypto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/2012-10-15-netsec-for-n00bs-part-iii-simple-intro-public-key-crypto&#34; title=&#34;Public Key Crypto&#34;&gt;Part III - Public Key Crypo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">NetSec for n00bs, part I: Password Storage</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/netsec-for-n00bs-part-i-password-storage/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/netsec-for-n00bs-part-i-password-storage/</id>
            <updated>2012-10-01T23:46:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In prepping for my interviews for my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/2012-09-25-from-n00b-to-engineer-in-one-year&#34; title=&#34;N00b to engineer&#34;&gt;newly acquired position&lt;/a&gt; with Red Hat for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://freeipa.org/page/Main_Page&#34; title=&#34;FreeIPA&#34;&gt;FreeIPA&lt;/a&gt; project, I did my own crash course in studying net security/applied cryptography.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a very important subject, and I feel a lot of new developers rely on frameworks or libraries to implement this sort of &amp;#39;stuff&amp;#39; for them without knowing what&amp;#39;s going on.  So for those who are oblivious (like I was) to NetSec topics and concerns, here is some lo-down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back when I was in banking, on my local desktop I had a password-protected Excel spreadsheet of logins &amp;amp; passwords.  I thought I was one step above just saving my passwords in a plain-text file.  Since then, the bank has implemented a one-password storage system (although it added about 30 seconds for each system we wanted to log into).  A password-locked file is quite easy to break if someone wanted to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, it is expected that passwords are stored on systems not in plain text, known as hashes.  A &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hash_function&#34; title=&#34;Wiki: Hash Function&#34;&gt;hash function&lt;/a&gt; is used to produce a hash.  This type of function is considered &amp;#39;one-way&amp;#39;, where the hash algorithm will take a plain text phrase (e.g. a password, or anything like a name, social security number, etc) and put out a hash, but would not be able to reverse it - take the hash and put out the plain text.  If you put a hash into a hash function, you would get a new hash.  Common types of hash functions: &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MD5&#34; title=&#34;wiki: md5&#34;&gt;MD5&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SHA-1&#34; title=&#34;Wiki: SHA-1&#34;&gt;SHA-1&lt;/a&gt;, [SHA-2][SHA2] &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MD5: &amp;quot;Message Digest Algorithm&amp;quot; produces a 128-bit hash.  While it is still widely used, since 1996 flaws have been discovered, making it very conceivable to break hashes. SHA-1: &amp;quot;Secure Hash Algorithm&amp;quot; produces a 160-bit hash.  Also widely used but also has security flaws in the algorithm itself (found around 2005). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SHA-2: consists of 4 hash functions producing 244, 256, 384 or 512 bit hashes. While no attacks have been successful on SHA-2, its algorithm is similar to SHA-1.  It&amp;#39;s still considered safe, but time is ticking. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These hash functions are still decent enough for message passing, just not password storage. Another hash algorithm, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bcrypt&#34; title=&#34;Wiki: Bcrypt&#34;&gt;Bcrypt&lt;/a&gt;, is thought to be more resistant to brute-force attacks.  This is because the algorithm adapts over time, basically lengthening the time it takes to create a hash, making it difficult to leverage increases in computer power. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;two-things-to-note-with-hash-functions&#34;&gt;Two things to note with hash functions:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;#39;t implement your own hash function. Just don&amp;#39;t.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speed should not be a factor when hashing passwords.  Basically, the longer it takes to hash a password, the longer it takes for brute-force attacks.  Speedier algorithms like MD5 or SHA-1 is fine for message-passing and source verification, but not good for storing sensitive information. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;is-a-hash-enough&#34;&gt;Is a hash enough?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. Storing a hash of a password isn&amp;#39;t enough.  If only a hash function is used to store a hash of plaintext, it&amp;#39;d be pretty easy to break it. For instance, if your password was &amp;#39;password&amp;#39;, it would have the same hash value as someone else who also uses the same password.  If someone were to break into a database of hashed passwords, it&amp;#39;d be very simple to do a quick frequency analysis, whichever hash is the most popular would probably be &amp;#39;password&amp;#39; or something like &amp;#39;1234&amp;#39;. This is essentially called a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rainbow_table&#34; title=&#34;Wiki: Rainbow table&#34;&gt;Rainbow Table&lt;/a&gt;, a set of reverse-engineered hashed passwords.  It is reasonable (in the amount of time spent, aka brute force) to create a rainbow table of passwords up to about 8 characters in length. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;so-then-what-now&#34;&gt;So then what now?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to combat the ease of creating rainbow tables, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salt_(cryptography)&#34; title=&#34;Wiki: Salt&#34;&gt;salt&lt;/a&gt; is added to the password before it is hashed.  It is very important that this salt is used only once, and is unique per user/password. For instance, if you use &amp;#39;password&amp;#39; as your password, your salt could be (which would be decided behind the scenes) &amp;#39;1\$0-1209-1!@fkjl&amp;#39;, so the input for the hash algorithm would be &amp;#39;password&amp;#39;+&amp;#39;1\$0-1209-1!@fkjl&amp;#39;.  Your salt would not be used for anyone else&amp;#39;s password.  So if someone else uses &amp;#39;password&amp;#39;, their salt would be something totally different, like &amp;#39;sl;--90(d%&amp;#39;, baring a different hash value for the same plaintext password. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;side-note&#34;&gt;Side note&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re interested in the history of cryptography, breaking passwords and frequency analysis as well as a great history on computing, I would highly suggest &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004IK8PLE/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B004IK8PLE&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=roglyn-20&#34; title=&#34;The Code Book&#34;&gt;The Code Book: The Science of Secrecy from Ancient Egypt to Quantum Cryptography&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/2012-10-03-netsec-for-n00bs-part-ii-ciphers-symmetric&#34; title=&#34;Symmetric Ciphers&#34;&gt;Part II - Ciphers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Operation: PyCon attendance</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/operation-pycon-attendance/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/operation-pycon-attendance/</id>
            <updated>2012-09-29T17:45:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thinking about going to &lt;a href=&#34;https://us.pycon.org/2013/&#34; title=&#34;PyCon&#34;&gt;PyCon&lt;/a&gt; for 2013?  Here are arguments to make for yourself and/or for your employer to go to PyCon this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;because-you39re-new-to-python&#34;&gt;Because you&amp;#39;re new to Python&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year&amp;#39;s PyCon is all about education.  The Program Committee is making an effort to include talks that cover all levels of experience; this includes talks, tutorials, and posters. Need  I remind you, the conference&amp;#39;s tag line is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change the future - education, outreach, politeness, respect, tenacity and vision&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beginners will probably get more benefit from tutorials than talks, and it&amp;#39;s perfectly okay to just sign up for tutorials.  If you&amp;#39;re hesitant, take a look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://us.pycon.org/2012/schedule/&#34; title=&#34;PyCon 2012 schedule&#34;&gt;2012&amp;#39;s schedule&lt;/a&gt;.  If there are even a couple of talks that seem interesting to you, you can be certain that similar subject matters will be spoken about for 2013. I also want to point out that talks and tutorials, while key to the conference, do not make the whole conference.  Spending hours in the Exhibit hall, talking to companies that use Python, learning about community outreach programs or open source projects are what makes the most out of a PyCon experience. Many companies will be recruiting, and perhaps that is intimidating, but it shouldn&amp;#39;t be.  Talk to them about the steps it takes to succeed at their company; find out what they&amp;#39;re looking for in an engineer.  This information can help you set goals for what you want to get out of learning Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;because-you39re-a-veteran-to-python&#34;&gt;Because you&amp;#39;re a veteran to Python&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be plenty of talks &amp;amp; tutorials on the other side of the spectrum: intermediate, advanced, and extreme/deep dive.  Python is ever evolving, always improving, so best not to quit learning.  There will be many challenging subjects spoken about, brilliant people holding conversations over their posters or post-talk/tutorial. Not to mention sprints.  Either join with the core language, or other Python projects that interest you.  Or perhaps this will give you the time and focus to code out that project you&amp;#39;ve always had on your todo list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;you39re-convinced-but-your-employer-might-not-be&#34;&gt;You&amp;#39;re convinced, but your employer might not be&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s cheap.  Tutorials are $150/200 each (early bird/on site) for 3 1/2-4 hours of intense learning.  The conference is $450/$600/$700 (corporate prices, early bird/regular/on site).  Comparatively, these huge conferences often go for far more than that. You will learn more in 9 days of tutorials, talks, and sprints than a year of reading books. Not only will you be exposed to trends, new technologies and ideas not yet written about, you have the opportunity to talk with other Python devs.  Another company had the same deployment issues you folks are having?  What about managing real time data? The hall way track presents many opportunities to have those conversations and knowledge transfers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A relavent tweet to part on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CFO to CEO: What happens if we invest in developing our people &amp;amp; then  they leave the company? CEO: What happens if we don&amp;#39;t and they stay? — Christina Haxton (@ChristinaHaxton) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ChristinaHaxton/status/252074201178066944&#34; title=&#34;Tweet&#34;&gt;September 29, 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">From n00b to Engineer in 1 year</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/from-n00b-to-engineer-in-one-year/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/from-n00b-to-engineer-in-one-year/</id>
            <updated>2012-09-25T17:45:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is my great pleasure (and squee!) to share with my friends, family, PyLadies, twitter nerds, Women Who Code&amp;#39;rs, DevChixen, Systers, and everyone else that I can now say: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;i-am-an-engineer.&#34;&gt;I am an Engineer.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/Joey_Chandler.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Joey &amp;amp; Chandler from Friends&#34; title=&#34;Moving Day&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the same person that once did not know the difference between a compiler and an interpreter, couldn&amp;#39;t explain wtf __init__.py files do, or conceive of generators versus iterators. The same person that took her way too long to admit that you can return more than one item in a function.  This is the same n00b that was once told by Leah Culver that one&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;...can&amp;#39;t just learn how to code without a CS degree.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I&amp;#39;d like to point out that it&amp;#39;s this exact industry that promotes and cultivates a culture &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; of ivory tower pedigrees but of free, easy access, and open source education.) Well my friends: by no means am I an expert, nor am I graduating from n00b status.  I am, however, taking my next step.  Drum roll... I am joining &lt;strong&gt;Red Hat&lt;/strong&gt; as a &lt;del&gt; black hat hacker&lt;/del&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Associate Software Engineer&lt;/strong&gt; working with OSS projects integrating RH&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://http://freeipa.org/page/Main_Page&#34; title=&#34;freeIPA&#34;&gt;identity and authorization&lt;/a&gt; down in Mountain View. Coding, community-building, applied cryptography, what could be better?  I&amp;#39;m just so honored and excited that my new manager and those I will be working with are willing to take a chance on me, and to give me the opportunity to grow into a field that I naively fell in love with (you can&amp;#39;t help who or what you fall in love with).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;oh-wait-there39s-moar&#34;&gt;Oh wait! there&amp;#39;s MOAR!&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m being given the awesome opportunity of a 2-month, unofficial &amp;#39;boot camp&amp;#39; at Red Hat&amp;#39;s &lt;strong&gt;Czech Republic&lt;/strong&gt; location in Brno.  HUZZAH! &lt;em&gt;Personal* *history insert&lt;/em&gt;: I lived in Prague, CZ for a semester in 2006. Loved it. Wrote my senior thesis on its transitional economy. Lived like a queen with beer being cheaper than water.  Utterly ecstatic to visit again. OK I&amp;#39;LL BE HONEST the real reason I&amp;#39;m joining RH is get my own &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.networkworld.com/Google%20Subnet/redhat%20penguin.gif&#34; title=&#34;Linux Penguin w fedora&#34;&gt;red fedora&lt;/a&gt;. #justkiddingnotreally&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll still lead PyLadies SF, live in SF, and be heavily involved in the Python community.  Just now employed, with health care, and a hard-earn title.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Brainstorm: Writing a PyCon proposal</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/brainstorm-writing-a-pycon-proposal/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/brainstorm-writing-a-pycon-proposal/</id>
            <updated>2012-08-27T23:46:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;OH MAN PYCON IS SO MUCH FUN.  &lt;em&gt;Right? I know!&lt;/em&gt;  I remember a tweet from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com/hmason&#34; title=&#34;Hilary Mason&amp;#39;s twitter&#34;&gt;Hilary Mason&lt;/a&gt; that it should be &amp;quot;PyCAAHHHNNN&amp;quot; (imagine with a Boston accent while flashing \m/ upon entrance). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever thought about submitting a proposal? &lt;em&gt;What? oh no, no no no.*Why not? *What would I talk about?  I have nothing to say!&lt;/em&gt; (Oddly, when starting out submitting talks to conferences, I never had that dialogue or PoV.  It was more like &amp;quot;I &amp;lt;3 the Python community. How can I be more involved?&amp;quot; and that&amp;#39;s how my ideation process started) (PS I love the verb &lt;em&gt;to ideate&lt;/em&gt;.  It&amp;#39;s great.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;so-how-about-this&#34;&gt; So how about this:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell me what talks you went to at previous years&amp;#39; PyCons that you found were pretty good (regardless of speaker performance)? What about: what would you like to see at PyCon &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; year? Ok.  You want to see those topics? Why don&amp;#39;t &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; write the talk you want to see? Bam, you have an idea. (cheeky lil&amp;#39; blogger, aren&amp;#39;t I?) No seriously: if you want to see a talk, write it yourself.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or: take what it is that you do with Python (professionally, hobby-wise, side-jobs, whatevs), and write a talk on it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is &lt;strong&gt;significant&lt;/strong&gt; interest in the &amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;Python in the Wild&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot; - such as, Python in corporations (product/services or used internally), &lt;em&gt;government&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;education&lt;/em&gt; (CS degrees, high school programs, communities), and &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt; (NASA, robotics). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is &lt;strong&gt;always&lt;/strong&gt; interest in popular topics, like deployment, big data, python packaging.  Not only do people have &lt;strong&gt;short memories&lt;/strong&gt;, but every year, it will be many people&amp;#39;s &lt;strong&gt;first PyCon&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What tends to be &lt;strong&gt;popular&lt;/strong&gt; are talks that compare frameworks/libraries/packages, critique a well-known/used tool/framework, and extreme talks (e.g. we&amp;#39;re getting down to the nitty gritty details of Twisted).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Topics that &lt;strong&gt;could do&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;surprisingly well&lt;/strong&gt; are security/cryptography, event-driven networking, and subjects that people should know about and probably default to industry standard, but don&amp;#39;t really know in depth.  &lt;strong&gt;Very interesting&lt;/strong&gt; subjects include &lt;em&gt;alternatives to giants&lt;/em&gt; like Django (e.g. Flask, Pyramid), or &lt;em&gt;where has Python failed.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;strong&gt;important&lt;/strong&gt; subject matters like &lt;em&gt;accessibility&lt;/em&gt; within Python, and &lt;em&gt;diversity&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;em&gt;community&lt;/em&gt; building. Not all talks at PyCon are technical (my head would explode), but are needed and well-respected nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;when-proposing-a-talk&#34;&gt;When proposing a talk:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Submit early.&lt;/strong&gt;  You know how many proposals the Program Committee has to read through?  Not to many right now.  There is more time and patience to give feedback, give a second look after the speaker responds/edits.  The committee also is not that tired yet. Submit on September 27th?  Dead tired.  Not really wanting to give feedback; just wanting this voting process over. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write an outline.&lt;/strong&gt;  Yes just do it.  It can be bare bones, but it helps a lot to see where you&amp;#39;re going with this talk, if there is enough meat behind this talk or if it&amp;#39;s too ambitious for the time slot.   Don&amp;#39;t write out your whole talk.  &lt;em&gt;My n00b confession: I wrote a 2-page single-spaced essay for my proposed talk at OSCON. /facepalm&lt;/em&gt; It also significantly helps the reviewer and you to &lt;strong&gt;associate length of time&lt;/strong&gt; per bullet/subpoint/etc.  The reviewer has a sense of where you&amp;#39;re going, if it can actually be a full talk or if it&amp;#39;s too long.  It also helps you frame your actual talk when you come to flesh it out (because no one &lt;em&gt;writes&lt;/em&gt; the damn talk before they propose it for the first time). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nervous about actually speaking? &lt;strong&gt;Find a partner&lt;/strong&gt;.  Either someone that shares your beginner level of speaking (both hold the burden of being nervous for your first talk) or someone that is already a seasoned speaker (you can relax a little!). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add links&lt;/strong&gt; to the &amp;#39;about you&amp;#39;/bio portion, or &lt;strong&gt;more context&lt;/strong&gt; in general about why you are the person to speak about this topic.  Did a project with Google Summer of Code?  Show the link. GitHub repo?  Love to see it.  Published a paper on the topic? Well it might not be &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt;, the fact that it&amp;#39;s there would give assurance :D. Remember though, provide the reviewers with more context on why you should be speaking on this topic (not just some random article you wrote about how lame PHP is (but it is lame).).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: it is &lt;strong&gt;not important&lt;/strong&gt; that you haven&amp;#39;t spoke at PyCon or another conference before.  But do prove that why you should now. Think &lt;strong&gt;posters&lt;/strong&gt; might be a better option for your first time presenting something at PyCon?  With a talk, you have about 30 minutes.  You can plan out what you&amp;#39;re going to say, how your talk might lead to certain questions (pro tip: leave some unanswered/unaddressed items from your talk, and look awesome when you know the answer if they&amp;#39;re asked).  After the talk, for questions you don&amp;#39;t know, you also have the forgiveness of the audience:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Oh actually, hmm, that&amp;#39;s a very good question.  I&amp;#39;m not sure I can address that here right now, but catch me after the talk.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(and then sprint away...:D) With a poster, you are defending your PhD thesis (practically), standing around for hours with some of the audience&amp;#39;s expectation of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;You know everything about this talk and I&amp;#39;m going to grill you because you&amp;#39;re stuck here.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be pretty demanding.  But it&amp;#39;s why posters are great for in-depth and/or unconventional topics.  There also a second shot at doing something with PyCon if you&amp;#39;re talk doesn&amp;#39;t get accepted since they are due Jan 15th. I think these hangouts that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/2012/08/25/pycon-proposal-brainstorming-via-google-hangout/&#34; title=&#34;PyCon Proposal Brainstorming via Google Hangout&#34;&gt;PyLadies&lt;/a&gt; did were productive; I got the feedback that they were helpful.  I also got the &amp;quot;zomg such a good idea but I can&amp;#39;t make it tonight.&amp;quot;  I&amp;#39;d like to see more, perhaps from the Program Committee itself (full disclosure, I am a part of the committee). We have 4 weeks until talk proposals are due.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Let&amp;#39;s help you give it your best shot. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">PyCon Proposal Brainstorming via Google Hangout</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/pycon-proposal-brainstorming-via-google-hangout/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/pycon-proposal-brainstorming-via-google-hangout/</id>
            <updated>2012-08-25T23:46:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ever thought about speaking? Want to give speaking at &lt;a href=&#34;http://us.pycon.org/2013&#34; title=&#34;PyCon 2013&#34;&gt;PyCon&lt;/a&gt; a shot, but not sure what to talk about? Even if you have a tiny inkling that you&amp;#39;d want to speak, beginner level or advanced, come to our workshop to get help brainstorming ideas &amp;amp; learn what makes a good proposal! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pycon2013workshop.eventbrite.com&#34; title=&#34;Eventbrite Link: PyLadies PyCon workshop @Google Hangout&#34;&gt;Join the PyLadies hangout&lt;/a&gt;, open to &lt;strong&gt;PyLadies&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;PyLaddies&lt;/strong&gt;, with help from PyLadies&amp;#39; leaders, previous years PyCon speakers &amp;amp; current Program Committee members (e.g. the folks that review proposals) to ideate, write, and submit your proposal to speak, give a tutorial, or a poster session at PyCon 2013. Space is limited by the Google Hangout technology. An invite link will be sent out about 15 minutes prior to the start time. For those in the Bay Area, be sure to check out the PyLadies San Francisco meetup, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/PyLadiesSF/events/76870962/&#34; title=&#34;PyLadies Meetup: Workshop for PyCon Talk Proposals&#34;&gt;Workshop: Talk Proposal Writing for PyCon&lt;/a&gt;, on Tuesday, August 28th. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eventbrite.com/event/4207274070?ref=ebtnebregn&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.eventbrite.com/custombutton?eid=4207274070&#34; alt=&#34;Button&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;moar-resources&#34;&gt;MOAR RESOURCES!&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://us.pycon.org/2013/speaking/speakatpycon/&#34; title=&#34;PyCon Info for Speakers&#34;&gt;More information in regards to speaking at PyCon.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pycon.blogspot.com/2012/08/what-talks-do-you-want-to-see-at-pycon.html&#34; title=&#34;PyCon Blog - what talks do you want to see&#34;&gt;Collection of suggested ideas from the Python community on the PyCon blog.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community suggestions from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://melitamihaljevic.blogspot.com/2012/08/pycon-2013-proposals-id-like-to-see.html&#34; title=&#34;Melita&amp;#39;s interested talks&#34;&gt;Melita Mihaljevic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://techblog.ironfroggy.com/2012/08/pycon-2013-posts-i-want-to-see.html&#34; title=&#34;Calvin&amp;#39;s interested talks&#34;&gt;Calvin Spealman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/r/Python/comments/ymy1f/what_pycon_talks_would_you_like_to_see/&#34; title=&#34;Reddit&amp;#39;s ideas&#34;&gt;a great Reddit thread&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://annaraven.blogspot.com/2012/08/pycon-proposals-id-like-to-see.html&#34; title=&#34;Ana Ravenscroft&amp;#39;s Ideas&#34;&gt;Anna Ravenscroft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://craigkerstiens.com/2012/06/19/pro-tips-for-conference-talks/&#34; title=&#34;Craig&amp;#39;s Pro tips for Talks&#34;&gt;Pro tips for conference talks via Craig Kerstiens&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.doughellmann.com/articles/how-tos/review-conference-proposal/index.html&#34; title=&#34;Doug&amp;#39;s Conference Proposal Review&#34;&gt;How PyCon proposals are reviewed via Doug Hellman&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Sadistic/Masochistic pleasure: Technical Interviews</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/sadistic-pleasure-technical-interviews/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/sadistic-pleasure-technical-interviews/</id>
            <updated>2012-08-15T23:46:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I was in high school, I was in &amp;quot;IB&amp;quot; math - the international equivalent to AP courses, except harder.  I really, really, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; enjoyed math.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My teacher would always mispronounce my name (&amp;quot;Wynn!&amp;quot;), but nonetheless, I loved the challenge.  I was the only one to receive 100% on the final exam, and one of a handful to take the IB exam.  I studied regularly, went over classmates&amp;#39; houses, worked through practice problems of vectors, differentiation, integration, goodness it was awesome.  I&amp;#39;d say that studying for this sort of stuff is very much like (if not the same concept) as the training I did for swimming: 2 hours/day in the pool, 6 days a week, extra hour each day of dry land training (side stepping the fact that right now, the most exercise I get is walking to/from cafes...). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it&amp;#39;s been years since my crush on high school math, that same feeling comes again when studying for technical interviews.  Few hours/day, every day, until the interview.  I recently had the excitement of having a technical phone screen with Google, and I thought it went pretty well.  Not in terms of I think I can make it to the next round (I don&amp;#39;t need to mention that the bar is set very high with them), but how I felt when comparing my last technical interview experience back in April.  I&amp;#39;d like to share how I prepared myself. I&amp;#39;ll mention that I my CV reflects a lot of PyLadies work, as well as knowledge of Python (natch), SQL, git, and working with different APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;how-i-prepared&#34;&gt;How I prepared:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had about a week for preparation (contrary to my previous one, where I had about two weeks).  Really, it had all depended on scheduling, but I tried to push it out as far as I could :D. First I read through a couple of Python resources just to become familiar with the &amp;#39;hidden gems&amp;#39; of the language that I may not use regularly or don&amp;#39;t have exposure to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  memorizing all of the language&amp;#39;s built in functions (easy peasy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  magic methods, as well as the difference between __str__ and __repr__&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  built in methods on data types (e.g. my_string.split())&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  difference between New Style &amp;amp; Classic classes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  range v xrange, generators v iterators, return v yield&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  default dicts w/ default factories, and other container datatypes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also reviewed some SQL crap too:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  difference between joins and outer left/right/both joins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  schema design (e.g. pk, fk, indices)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I spent a lot of time doing algorithms, graph transversals, data structures (without Python&amp;#39;s help), etc.  I used Gayle Laakmann McDowell&amp;#39;s book: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Cracking-Coding-Interview-Programming-Questions/dp/098478280X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1344972927&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=cracking+the+coding+interview&#34; title=&#34;Amazon link to Cracking the Coding Interview book&#34;&gt;Cracking the Coding Interview&lt;/a&gt; since it gives a very well laid out path to study for the typical technical interview.  I found that Palantir (a tech/finance/info company that I have a hard crush on) has a great&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.palantir.com/2011/09/how-to-rock-an-algorithms-interview/&#34; title=&#34;Palantir&amp;#39;s interview advice&#34;&gt;how-to&lt;/a&gt; on succeeding their technical/algorithm interviews (and I feel that applies to all aggressive tech companies).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My process each day would be to warm up with a couple of easy problems, then go onto a more difficult graph or algorithm problem.  A lot reflects Gayle&amp;#39;s book, and in that book she uses Java (hence some of these problems can be easily implemented in Python with no thought).  I&amp;#39;ll leave you to get her awesome book in order to read best approaches &amp;amp; the answers (literally, every example problem has a solution in the book, it&amp;#39;s great).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In loose order of difficulty, starting with what I&amp;#39;d have for breakfast and ending towards what made me skip meals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strings/Arrays&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  determine a string w/ all unique characters (both w/ and w/o
additional data structures)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  write an algo to determine if a string is a palindrome&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  write an algo such that if an element in an MxN matrix is 0, its
entire row &amp;amp; column are set to 0.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Linked Lists (without Python&amp;#39;s awesomesauce)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  creating a linked list&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  find the kth element of a singly linked list&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  remove duplicates from unsorted linked list&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stacks &amp;amp; Queues&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  implement a stack/queue (and know the diff between each)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  use a single array to implement three stacks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  in addition to push/pop for a stack/queue, also design a min
function to return the min node (operating in o(1) time)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  towers of Hanoi problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trees and graphs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  define a function to check if a binary tree is balanced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  write an algo that creates a binary search tree w/ minimal
height&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Breadth/depth-first searches (not too hard esp after stacks &amp;amp;
queues)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  implement a suffix tree&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Dijkstra&amp;#39;s algorithm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sorting &amp;amp; Searching&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  you have two sorted arrays, A &amp;amp; B where A is large enough buffer
at the end to hold B.  write a method to merge B into A in
sorted order.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  find the index of a given integer in an array (unsorted)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;moar graphs, algos and random but good&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  write a power function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  implement an atoi function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  write a simple caesar cipher (both encoding &amp;amp; decoding)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  write a greedy algorithm that returns amount of change in coins
(quarters, dimes, nickels, pennies)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  write an algorithm/mini program that, given a maze, a start &amp;amp; an
end point, returns the path(s) needed to exit the maze (this was
not fun to do at 8pm the night before the interview, but it is a
damn good problem to attack).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, perhaps someone could enlighten me, I wasn&amp;#39;t able to get &lt;a href=&#34;http://community.topcoder.com/tc&#34; title=&#34;top coder&#34;&gt;TopCoder&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s java applet running (although I could months ago). Those algo problems are great, challenging, and appeal to different levels.  TopCoder&amp;#39;s problems would be a fantastic help to those prepping for the in-person technical interview.  Hopefully I&amp;#39;m the only one with the issue. A week or so after my interview, someone posted on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/r/learnprogramming/comments/xwd16/had_a_technical_phone_interview_today_for_an/&#34; title=&#34;a self-post on reddit&#34;&gt;/r/learnprogramming&lt;/a&gt; in reddit what questions s/he was asked during a technical phone interview.  Very helpful (note that the interviewee is a C++ person interviewing for an entry level software engineer position at a mid-sized, well-known company):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  What kind of data structure would you use to hold an arbitrary amount of objects in which retrieval is not an issue?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Follow up: what are the advantages and disadvantages of using a linked list over a dynamic array structure? [good time to talk about Big-O performance]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Describe the main properties of a binary search tree.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  What would happen if you inserted a sorted list into a binary search tree?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Follow up: how can you avoid this problem?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Say you want to retrieve from a data set a person&amp;#39;s name based on an alphanumeric ID number. What kind of data structure would you use?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Compare a hash table and a map type structure and their big-O performance on various common functionality (search, insert, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  What is the worst case retrieval time for a hash table and how can this happen?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Briefly describe object oriented programming and it&amp;#39;s main principles (MAKE SURE TO SAY: encapsulation, inheritance, and  polymorphism, (and abstraction if you want)).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  He specifically asked me to elaborate more on encapsulation and polymorphism.  Why is polymorphism useful?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  What is a join and an outer join? (SQL)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading through those redditor&amp;#39;s interview questions, I actually felt that I can answer the majority of them.  Actually I didn&amp;#39;t know what encapsulation was, but luckily I wasn&amp;#39;t the one in the hot seat for that interview, and I googled it :D.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;my-weak-points-that-i-will-work-on&#34;&gt;My weak points that I will work on:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Understanding what can be done to improve runtimes of an algorithm  (not just be able to tell the runtime).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Being more confident in my understanding of concepts.  For instance, I know what a RESTful API is, but how do I spit it back coherently? Same with explaining git.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Calm the f&amp;amp;ck down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;things-i-thought-i-did-well-in&#34;&gt;Things I thought I did well in:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Wrote &amp;amp; instantiated a class that would be used to make a graph, using the requested private variables/methods (he seemed a little impressed).  Although I do believe I mixed up new style v classic. /facepalm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Talking through each and every damn thing I was saying and writing (was not easy the first time).  And going back through what I coded to test simple cases &amp;amp; fixed typos/errors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  My understanding of repr v str (finally...).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Simple schema writing (from the first interview).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Before coding, switched the font/size to courier 8 (seriously, red flag to them if not using a fixed-width font when gdocs defaults to a variable-width one).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m certainly not counting on going further from that interview.  I quite like the set up I have now doing contracting with a friend&amp;#39;s consulting + Harvard&amp;#39;s project, and I seem to walk into new opportunities (then again, this is the Bay Area). Thankfully I&amp;#39;m also able to contribute to open source, give talks &amp;amp; go to conferences, put on workshops and events, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But hey - you&amp;#39;d understand if Google came calling, right?  I actually look forward to the day where I can go in and code on a whiteboard, but that will take a lot more studying, understanding of more complex algorithms, better understanding of runtimes, perhaps systems architecture.  For those PyLadies and Women Who Code&amp;#39;ers in the Bay Area, WWC is hosting a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Women-Who-Code-SF/events/77224932/&#34; title=&#34;Women Who Code tech interviewing event&#34;&gt;Technical Interview evening talk/mini-workshop&lt;/a&gt; with Gayle Laakmann McDowell next week.  We&amp;#39;re also looking for mentors (and food sponsors!), so hit me up if you&amp;#39;re interested! &lt;strong&gt;Update: &lt;/strong&gt;I was told not to divulge what questions I received from the interviewer as it reflects poorly.  So, let me just say: what I studied aligned pretty well with what I was asked :D  I just...wish I had a better memory! Another resource given to me: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.interviewstreet.com/challenges/&#34; title=&#34;Interview Street Challenges&#34;&gt;Interview Street&lt;/a&gt;, and I forgot &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.careercup.com/&#34; title=&#34;Career Cup: Programming Interview Questions&#34;&gt;CareerCup&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Our generation&#39;s Legos</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/our-generations-legos/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/our-generations-legos/</id>
            <updated>2012-07-28T17:44:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;First time I heard about raspberry pi was through twitter.  I thought: Oh I bet that&amp;#39;s a cute name for a new python module.  Didn&amp;#39;t look into it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I overheard a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; dedicated PyLady saying &amp;quot;OMG my Raspberry Pi shipped today!&amp;quot; Wait, a module shipped?  She doesn&amp;#39;t develop python modules.  Is this a physical thing? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, weeks later, I asked another friend, &amp;quot;What is this Raspberry Pi?&amp;quot; The world stopped to him.  &amp;quot;What, are you serious?&amp;quot; he responded.  &amp;quot;Yeah…?&amp;quot;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly I wasn&amp;#39;t getting &amp;quot;it.&amp;quot;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I preceded to get educated in &amp;quot;it.&amp;quot; Sure, I thought - that&amp;#39;s cool, a credit card sized computer.  It didn&amp;#39;t seem that big of a deal to me - that the kind of stuff iPhones &amp;amp; Androids run on, wicked small computers.  It&amp;#39;s \$35 too - not bad, but it still didn&amp;#39;t appeal to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then after a few days after that conversation - it hit me.  Holy sh*t this is a revolutionary idea.  Holy crap, I get &amp;quot;it.&amp;quot;  Now I understood why there was a 3 month wait time for ordering. To share this enlightenment, I can&amp;#39;t simply say &amp;quot;imagine the possibilities.&amp;quot;  A lot of people require handholding for some creative thinking.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me continue my thought process: I hadn&amp;#39;t really been &amp;#39;into&amp;#39; computers beyond the use of them until about 9 or 10 months ago.  I was damn good at my shortcuts around Excel, my Google-fu skills, my typing speed thanks to AIM, but I didn&amp;#39;t really care about what was going on underneath my laptop&amp;#39;s keyboard. September 2011 I took my first computer science course.  &lt;em&gt;Not&lt;/em&gt; because I was interested in learning to program, but because I needed to know programming to apply to graduate school for financial engineering.  December 2011 I finished with an A- and never looked at finance again. In my new life, my &amp;#39;finally found my passion&amp;#39; mindset, I haven&amp;#39;t stopped consuming programming, learning computers, understanding security risks, teaching others and myself python, speaking about it, etc… My 2008 MBP died earlier this year.  It comes back to life every once and a while, but when it does kick the bucket for one last time, oh boy will I perform an autopsy.  I will dissect, rip apart, hack, and reuse anything and everything. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter: Raspberry Pi.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raspberry Pi appeals to hackers, programmers, the child still inside of all of us.  It&amp;#39;s our generation&amp;#39;s Legos. I&amp;#39;m going to take that piece of computer board fruit and I&amp;#39;m going to hack the sh*t out of it.  I&amp;#39;m poor, so I can&amp;#39;t buy even the cheapest of monitors. OH WAIT I have an old MBP lying around.  Not sure how that will go but I will try, and I will learn how monitors work in the process. I have legos (yes…just bought a space shuttle kit).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know what I&amp;#39;m going to do?  Try something out with PyGame and my lego wheels (I feel sorry for the cat and the impending annoyance I will cause him). I plan to make a home security system - quite needed living in the Mission of SF.  How? not sure, but  it&amp;#39;s damn well possible.  Probably hook up one of the speakers that I have from 1999, or steal one from my MBP.  It&amp;#39;ll probably be a hack job at first - faulty wires exposed, false alarms and annoyed neighbors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OH goodness what about a voice-command thing tailored to my voice?  &amp;quot;Start Pandora&amp;quot; (sorry Spotify).  &amp;quot;Start picture slideshow.&amp;quot;  &amp;quot;Turn off lights.&amp;quot;  &amp;quot;Turn on coffee machine.&amp;quot;  &amp;quot;Remind me to take my meds.&amp;quot;  MY OWN STARTREK LIFE. I&amp;#39;ll get bothered by how relatively slow Debian Squeeze will be (the OS you&amp;#39;ll have to download yourself).  There goes my weekend of learning/writing linux kernels. Hmm after all these thoughts, I stepped back for a second.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This computer isn&amp;#39;t just for me, and for people like me.  A \$35 computer in the hands (literal hands!) of children.  Not some mystifying 1/2 in x 13 in x 9in slap of aluminum w/ a keyboard. Small a\$\$ computer + PyGame + Legos (+ Arduino maybe) = only limited by imagination.  Perhaps a child can amuse a cat&amp;#39;s afternoon like me.  Or perhaps strap it on one of those small, build-your-own rockets (I LOVED those as a kid!), shoot it up in the air, and record flight data (is that possible? f^ck who cares, I&amp;#39;m going to do it now). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if we and our kids take this opportunity to put this computer in the hands of developing nations&amp;#39; children?   I&amp;#39;d chip in \$35 to send this to an eager child with little access to it him/herself.  Why don&amp;#39;t we + our kids preprogram &amp;amp; preload it with learning tools, with Khan academy videos?  Why not send one monitor down, a bunch of cables, and Raspberry Pis w/ edu videos for a whole village?  I&amp;#39;ll throw in some legos in there. Oh man, you know what the best part of it is?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python is on Debian Squeeze.  The makers of RP &amp;amp; the OS couldn&amp;#39;t have selected an easier language for the world to learn.  Looking at how far _I_ got in 1/2 a year of learning Python, and I do feel the hindrance of an aging brain.  Imagine the pace at a child learns.  Let me say that again: Imagine the pace that a child learns.  Just think. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok let me connect the dots for you:  Is your company hiring? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raspberry Pi is this a simple, evolutionary piece of hardware that has the potential to &lt;em&gt;revolutionize&lt;/em&gt; the state of education.  We are already experiencing the logarithmic rate of growth from technology.  Education is piggy-backing along.  And accessibility to education can&amp;#39;t and &lt;strong&gt;won&amp;#39;t&lt;/strong&gt;be left behind.   We as a community, Python, engineering, technology, etc) have this amazing opportunity to put Raspberry Pis in the hands of many.  Sure, some people won&amp;#39;t see the importance of it, like I didn&amp;#39;t at first. But those that do and that will, you have given them the push, the nudge that everyone needs once and a while to just &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; something.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hack at something.  Create something.  Revisit that child in him/herself.  Pass it on to an actual child. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I graduated, I got a very piss-poor commencement speech. Nothing inspiring, nothing moving.  But one of the new deans was not too bad.  Everyone liked him and his energy that he brought to our tinybusiness school.  He said, and repeated throughout his speech, &amp;quot;Do great things.&amp;quot;  Cheesy, I know.  I walked, received my diploma, and promptly got drunk. Four years after graduating, I&amp;#39;ve passively noticed thislittle voice, a little engine-who-could voice, repeating &amp;quot;Do greatthings.&amp;quot;  Here I am, internally lit by this motto. I hope this firecatches elsewhere, too.  Do great things.  Here&amp;#39;s our opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Moar Bookmarks!</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/moar-bookmarks/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/moar-bookmarks/</id>
            <updated>2012-07-27T23:45:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Seeing how my previous &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/2012-05-20-gold-nuggets-my-bookmarks-collection&#34; title=&#34;Gold Nuggets&#34;&gt;bookmarks post&lt;/a&gt; was well-received, here is MOAR!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A collection of helpful tutorials, tools, and libraries for folks learning Python/how to code, or looking to improve and explore their skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;tutorials-amp-how-tos&#34;&gt;Tutorials &amp;amp; How-tos&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://krondo.com/?page_id=1327&#34; title=&#34;Intro to Twisted&#34;&gt;Introduction to Twisted&lt;/a&gt;: A thorough introduction to Twisted and Asyncronous programming in Python. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://try.github.com/levels/1/challenges/1&#34; title=&#34;tryGit&#34;&gt;tryGit&lt;/a&gt;: Learn Git with GitHub&amp;amp; Codeschool&amp;#39;s new tutorial. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.konstruktor.ee/blog/django-the-undocumented-settings/&#34; title=&#34;Django: the Undocumented Settings&#34;&gt;Django: The Undocumented Settings&lt;/a&gt;: Tricks when writing the settings.py file for Django. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://devcenter.heroku.com/articles/django&#34; title=&#34;tutorial for Django on Heroku&#34;&gt;Getting Started with Django from Heroku&lt;/a&gt;: A tutorial using Django and deploying with Heroku.  Assumes some knowledge of virtual environments. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://people.csail.mit.edu/pgbovine/python/&#34; title=&#34;Online Python Tutorial&#34;&gt;Online Python Tutor&lt;/a&gt;: Learn &amp;amp; Practice programming in your browser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://craigkerstiens.com/2012/06/19/pro-tips-for-conference-talks/&#34; title=&#34;Conference Pro Tips&#34;&gt;Protips on Conference Talks&lt;/a&gt;: Thinking about giving a talk at a conference? Here is some great advice on how to rock it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;tools&#34;&gt;Tools&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://opensourcehacker.com/2012/05/11/sublime-text-2-tips-for-python-and-web-developers/&#34; title=&#34;Sublime Text 2 for Python &amp;amp; Web Developers&#34;&gt;Sublime for Python and Web Developers&lt;/a&gt;: How to squeeze more power out of one of the most popular, light weight text editors for Python.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shortcutfoo.com/app/tutorial/sublimetext&#34; title=&#34;Sublime Shortcuts&#34;&gt;Sublime Short cuts&lt;/a&gt;**: Learn to get more out of the latest text editor. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.corntab.com/pages/crontab-gui&#34; title=&#34;Crontab GUI&#34;&gt;Visual Crontab Editor&lt;/a&gt;: Easily create crontab syntax for your Linux or Unix servers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;libraries&#34;&gt;Libraries&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[PEP-8 Style Guide Checker][PEP8]: Are you writing code according to the standard Python guidelines?  Have no idea?  Try out this library.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/BrewerHimself/Logr&#34; title=&#34;Simple Python blogger&#34;&gt;Logr&lt;/a&gt;: Simple Python blogger. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kennethreitz/legit&#34; title=&#34;Git for Humans&#34;&gt;Git Legit&lt;/a&gt;: Git for Humans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">PyLadies @ OSCON</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/pyladies-oscon/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/pyladies-oscon/</id>
            <updated>2012-07-26T23:45:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had the wonderful opportunity to bring up a few fellow PyLadies to Portland, Oregon for O&amp;#39;Reilly&amp;#39;s Open Source Convention.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the help of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psf.org&#34; title=&#34;PSF&#34;&gt;Python Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, we were able to bring along swag including stickers, postcards of information on how to start a local PyLadies chapter, and a new banner. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an interesting experience.  There was a lot of excitement for the conference; the open-source community is fantastic to be a part of. But what was weird was that I felt there were not a lot of Pythonistas there.  Similarly, I felt PyLadies&amp;#39; presence wasn&amp;#39;t as well received as I originally anticipated.  I heard a lot of people walk by, asking &amp;quot;pe... pilates? what&amp;#39;s pilates?&amp;quot; Interestingly enough, this gave me an event idea: &amp;quot;PyLadies does Pilates!&amp;quot; :D &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk that I gave was a little awkward, too. Not many people showed up (bummer), and the majority of the folks that did were women.  That was actually pretty awesome to witness, but it was sort of preaching to the choir. :) One thing I do thoroughly enjoy is the conversation &amp;amp; questions that come after my talks.  I&amp;#39;m always blown away how everyone wants to get more women involved, and how welcoming new ideas and thoughts are to do such thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of Open Source - be sure to check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/PyLadiesSF/&#34; title=&#34;PyLadies SF Meetup Group&#34;&gt;PyLadiesSF&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s upcoming events:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/PyLadiesSF/events/73638942/&#34; title=&#34;Learn to Contribute to OSS event&#34;&gt;Learn to Contribute to Open Source&lt;/a&gt;, and&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/PyLadiesSF/events/73639302/&#34; title=&#34;Django + PyLadiesSF Sprint&#34;&gt;PyLadies + Community Django Sprint&lt;/a&gt; to improve the well-known Django tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Moar Womenz at DjangoCon US!</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/moar-womenz-at-djangocon-us/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/moar-womenz-at-djangocon-us/</id>
            <updated>2012-07-25T17:44:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;h4 id=&#34;change-the-ratio-at-djangocon-2012&#34;&gt;Change the Ratio at DjangoCon 2012&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to go to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.djangocon.us/&#34; title=&#34;DjangoCon US 2012&#34;&gt;DjangoCon 2012&lt;/a&gt; in Washington, D.C. -- or know a talented developer who does -- but cannot attend due to financial hardship, please &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/viewform?formkey=dDc1X2hrUGJVRGdEWnRjTklxR2tSNFE6MQ#gid=0&#34; title=&#34;FinAid&#34;&gt;apply for financial aid through DjangoCon&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;And&lt;/strong&gt;, if you&amp;#39;re a PyLady (as opposed to a PyLaddie), please indicate that you would like to be considered for a&lt;strong&gt; PyLadies grant&lt;/strong&gt; on that form. This year&amp;#39;s conference goes from Sept. 3 - Sept. 9. The deadline for the PyLadies grant submission is &lt;strong&gt;Friday, August 3rd&lt;/strong&gt;.  We apologize for the short notice, but we know that people need time to make travel plans/request days off from work, etc.  You will hear from us by the end of the week after applications are submitted. If you know of a talented, deserving female developer who might benefit greatly from attending DjangoCon, email &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:info@pyladies.com&#34; title=&#34;Email to Info&#34;&gt;us&lt;/a&gt;.  We&amp;#39;ll do our best to help as many women as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to the DjangoCon organizers and the Python Software Foundation for helping the PyLadies manage this program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;sponsors&#34;&gt;Sponsors:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this program is to bring new talent to the Djangosphere by supporting developers and giving them opportunity to make connections in the community. Your support of PyLadies’ outreach efforts will pay off hugely over the long term by improving the diversity of the industry as a whole. Companies &amp;amp; Individuals are invited to offer funding for talented developers who have demonstrated or show potential for a serious commitment to diversity in the Django commnunity. Donations will go through the &lt;a href=&#34;http://python.org/psf&#34; title=&#34;PSF&#34;&gt;Python Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, and are thus &lt;strong&gt;tax-deductible&lt;/strong&gt;, yeah! Please email &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:sponsors@pyladies.com&#34; title=&#34;Email to Sponsors&#34;&gt;sponsors@pyladies.com&lt;/a&gt; if you&amp;#39;d like to send a woman developer to DjangoCon.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">A memorable EuroPython, for the better</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/a-memorable-europython-for-the-better/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/a-memorable-europython-for-the-better/</id>
            <updated>2012-07-12T23:45:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;EuroPython marked many memorable experiences for me, as a PyLady, as a member of the Python community, and as a newbie to coding &amp;amp; programming. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it is widely known and very well accepted that the folks at EuroPython did a fantastic job in organizing the whole conference. Every detail was well thought out.  Coming from 7000+ miles away, I did not feel like a foreigner.  Little things, including inviting me to join them in the evening a couple days before the conference; having cordial side conversations; and making connections &amp;amp; introductions, it all really helped me out. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be given an opportunity to speak about what I&amp;#39;ve been doing with PyLadies in San Francisco and Women Who Code is fantastic; and to have it elevated to a keynote was all the more surreal.  I thought it was pretty well received by the audience.  Many folks asked really good, difficult questions; things that needed to be discussed.  My approach to the talk was to provoke some thought in the audience without really alienating them.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet many still wanted to get to the elephant in the room: &amp;quot;what are we doing that we don&amp;#39;t know we&amp;#39;re doing?&amp;quot; Long answer short: It&amp;#39;s not Python community-specific, but how we bring general societal norms into the community.  We, the python community, have been very open minded with who joins us.  I&amp;#39;m not sure why, if it&amp;#39;s a precedent that Guido set, if it&amp;#39;s the type of people the language attracts, or if it&amp;#39;s because it&amp;#39;s the model child of FOSS. It&amp;#39;s certainly a breath of fresh air compared to the likes of Java or C (no offense, well, maybe...). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another hot question was &amp;quot;Is Guido&amp;#39;s t-shirt, Python is for Girls, sexist?&amp;quot;  From the point of view of a woman, it ostracizes me.  It feels like someone is trying to dress up programming with the color pink.  Or like Lego trying to appeal to girls with &lt;a href=&#34;http://shop.lego.com/en-US/Stephanie-s-Outdoor-Bakery-3930&#34; title=&#34;Lego Backery&#34;&gt;it&amp;#39;s easy-bake oven twist&lt;/a&gt;.  But when talking to Guido one-on-one, as I would have thought, he of course didn&amp;#39;t mean it to be offensive.  Rather, he means to challenge the programmer paradigm. After the keynote, many approached me.  One gal from &lt;a href=&#34;http://geekgirlscarrots.pl&#34; title=&#34;Geek Girl Carrots&#34;&gt;geekgirlscarrots.pl&lt;/a&gt; gave me the greatest greeting and sincerest thank you I&amp;#39;ve heard.  Men came up asking for help and ideas how to get more women involved in their communities back home.  I felt this talk was very well received (despite being so nervous for it!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most-talked about event, in my opinion (probably because I was the center of it), was the incident outline in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/words/2012-07-05-really&#34; title=&#34;Really&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;. Namely, a conference attendee tweeted something offensive in reference&lt;br&gt;
to #pyladies, I called him out, addressed it with the EuroPython organizers, and allowed a discussion (if you can call it that) happen on my blog. My first thought about that event: The organizers of EuroPython handled it exceptionally well.  I went to the venue early before the conference started for the day, and they were already aware of the tweet (and I assume my reaction to it via twitter or my blog, as well).  They were very diligent in consulting the appropriate people on the EuroPython/Python Italia board.  The result was, I felt, adequate in addressing the situation.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/pwang/status/221172889813131264&#34; title=&#34;Apology 1&#34;&gt;A public apology&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/pwang/status/221196983031963654&#34; title=&#34;Apology 2&#34;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;, actually) from the attendee via twitter and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/2012/07/05/really/comment-page-1/#comment-5125&#34; title=&#34;Apology Comment&#34;&gt;on my blog&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/europython/status/221201258424442881&#34; title=&#34;EuroPython Stance&#34;&gt;public stance&lt;/a&gt; on their &lt;a href=&#34;https://ep2012.europython.eu/code-of-conduct&#34; title=&#34;EuroPython CoC&#34;&gt;Code of Conduct&lt;/a&gt; via twitter, and plenty of reassurance in private. I can&amp;#39;t stress enough that the organizers were very respectful, and did exactly what I thought should be done.  This is exactly why there needs to be a CoC at conferences, and why the Python community is very adamant about signing the &lt;a href=&#34;http://letsgetlouder.com/&#34; title=&#34;Lets Get Louder&#34;&gt;Let&amp;#39;s Get Louder campaign&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;d like to quote a comment on the Let&amp;#39;s Get Louder campaign from someone who I met at EuroPython, but didn&amp;#39;t know at the time of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/r/Python/comments/vroj4/python_programmers_sign_pledge_to_only/c579eeb&#34; title=&#34;Hynek&amp;#39;s Comment&#34;&gt;when this was posted&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s amazing how people who have never been affected by any type of discrimination decide for the rest, that it’s not a big deal and not our problem. But it *is* our problem. Because *this* is *our* community. And I will not tolerate that people get discriminated or harassed ... without any reaction from *inside* the community. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because that’s bad for our community. For every single person of us. A code of conduct is not about giving women or other minorities the power to get people they dislike out of conferences just by accusing them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So stop bringing that up. It is a firm statement by the organizers and everyone who decides to take part of such an event that *we* as a community value every member of it and don’t want assholes make them feel not welcome. That if someone harasses them we’ll be there for them and won’t just shrug our shoulders and/or relay cowardly responsibilities to ominous third parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this incident happened, I &lt;del&gt;teared up a bit&lt;/del&gt; cried. Not because I took the tweet to heart, but because I knew that I was in a safe space, here at the conference.  I had this comment in the back of my mind already, and to reflect back to it gave me some comfort.  I was comfortable showing up to the conference, having normal conversations with folks, and did not feel ostracized. The apology, while I don&amp;#39;t doubt the sincerity, showed lack of cognizance &amp;amp; self awareness of the issue at hand. For clarity: some people don&amp;#39;t get it.  From another community that I shared this incident with, this response hits the point pretty well.  I want to illustrate a female point of view that I heavily agree with, but can&amp;#39;t seem to voice it as well as her.  With her permission, I am posting anonymously:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without #Pyladies it&amp;#39;s not a joke, it&amp;#39;s just a contentless anecdote. The hash tag wasn&amp;#39;t just accidental or in poor taste.  It would still have been sexist and offensive and objectifying and rape-culturish if he had tagged it &amp;quot;#ladies?&amp;quot;or &amp;quot;#Wife?&amp;quot;  (God forbid we say so though, or expect men to actually think about women as people instead of blow job machines.)  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is extra-special-nasty because he implied that specifically technical women who were where he was right then are *still* nothing more than objects for his sexual pleasure, and so it becomes a specific and personal threat/dehumanization of actual, specific women whom he could probably see at the time.  That is offensive and sexist and objectifying *and* creepy and discouraging and alienating and perpetuates the culture that creates the gross gender imbalances in our industry. Until these dudes start deconstructing their thoughts themselves, I will deconstruct their thoughts for them.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they don&amp;#39;t like what their jokes say about them, they should start thinking before they speak now shouldn&amp;#39;t they? It is entirely possible to make dirty jokes that don&amp;#39;t rely on a blind sense of entitlement to sexual relations with the generic category of &amp;quot;women&amp;quot; (or any other generic category, for that matter.)  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, &amp;quot;Sucked the marrow out of my osso bucco at #Europython.  Waiter said I will have &amp;quot;very good orgasm.&amp;quot; He was right. #Flexible&amp;quot; Or &amp;quot;Sucked the marrow out of my osso bucco Waiter said I will have &amp;quot;very good orgasm.&amp;quot; Wasn&amp;#39;t practicing for me #LoveYouDear&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;#39;t an overreaction; this was a perfect situation to bring to light the type of incidents women do face.  Sure, maybe one comment can be easily brushed off.  But it isn&amp;#39;t one, it&amp;#39;s many.  From both in private at home with silly, innocuous jokes, to a$$hat comments made in public.  It adds up.  The general creepy comments from being the only female at a table drinking; the hurtful, disrespectful, and gaslighting tweets &amp;amp; blog comments; the crass jokes; the &amp;quot;calm down, just breathe. You&amp;#39;re overreacting&amp;quot; conversation (!). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For simple, lightbulb moments that I&amp;#39;ve witnessed some men get, it&amp;#39;s gratifying and reassuring.  It&amp;#39;s the reason I&amp;#39;m speaking.  The soft &amp;quot;a-ha&amp;quot; speaks loudly. The support that I got that evening and the rest of the conference was amazing. Some went up to bat on behalf of me/PyLadies/women in tech.  Some simply asked how I was doing. Overall, I could not have asked for a better experience.  I met many prolific and awesome people in the Python community.  I&amp;#39;ve made friends that I know will last beyond the sunny days of Florence.  And I&amp;#39;ve made a pretty hard dent in my liver.  I&amp;#39;m looking forward to next year.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">You ask why I need to talk about women in the Python community?</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/really/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/really/</id>
            <updated>2012-07-05T17:44:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;h4 id=&#34;update&#34;&gt;Update:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the pseudo/half baked apology from the original offender, I&amp;#39;ve decided to remove any identifying characteristics. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had an amazing talk on Wednesday, July 4th at EuroPython.  I maintained my positive attitude; I tried not to alienate the audience (especially the majority being male); I tried to keep the conversation going during the question &amp;amp; answer session and afterwards.  Many men had fantastic questions regarding my subject: increasing female engagement in the Python community. I returned home tonight to find this: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/pwang_tweet.png&#34; alt=&#34;twitter&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I JUST gave a talk on yesterday about women &amp;amp; Python. &lt;strong&gt;This dude asked me a question on the things men do unconsciously.&lt;/strong&gt;   WHAT THE HELL I DON&amp;#39;T EVEN! My thoughts are to be continued later after I&amp;#39;ve calmed down and addressed this with the organizers. &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">EuroPython 2012: Day 1</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/europython-2012-day-1/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/europython-2012-day-1/</id>
            <updated>2012-07-03T23:45:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re a Python enthusiast, and you&amp;#39;re &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; at EuroPython, you&amp;#39;re missing out, I&amp;#39;m sorry to say.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only has the conference organizers put on a near flawless first day, they provided attendees with amazing food for thought with a fantastic program of keynotes to kick off the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/me_europython_slide.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Me EuroPython Slide&#34; title=&#34;Me!&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone was a bit start struck that Guido van Rossum was here; it&amp;#39;s funny to see folks put him on a little bit of a pedestal when he&amp;#39;s a normal nerd like the rest of us.  And naturally, he was wearing his favorite shirt: Python is for Girls.  (f&amp;amp;ck yea!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Side note:&lt;/strong&gt; Female attendance of EuroPython has &lt;strong&gt;doubled&lt;/strong&gt; since last year, from 4% to 8%, while the overall attendance has increased about 100 people, or about 15% from last year (a rough estimate from collected conversations).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guido&amp;#39;s talk was very similar to his closing keynote at PyCon US this year, Not the State of the Union.  What I found more interesting was the moderated Q&amp;amp;A he did towards the end of the day.  More on that in a second...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ep2012.europython.eu/conference/p/alex-martelli&#34; title=&#34;Alex Martelli&#34;&gt;Alex Martelli&lt;/a&gt; did a talk on the fantastic subject of Ask for Forgiveness, not for Permission, inspired by Grace Hopper.  It was very awesome and heart-warming to hear the crowd on twitter really welcome and embrace that line of thought, both because it&amp;#39;s a great motto to live by (esp for engineers), as well as a very prominent and well-respected woman said it.  Only, he used Apple&amp;#39;s version of Comic Sans on his slides: Chalkboard.  Not that forgivable... (although I&amp;#39;ve committed that crime as well in my Python study group slides *hides head in shame*).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I didn&amp;#39;t realize that Martelli was the author of Python in a Nutshell, and co-edited w/ this wife, Anna, the Python Cookbook. I should have lugged that door stopper to get it signed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ep2012.europython.eu/conference/p/febo-cincotti&#34; title=&#34;febo Cincotti&#34;&gt;Febo Cincotti&lt;/a&gt; presented on the progression neuroscience has made in allowing those who have absolutely no way to communicate without the help of computers in his talk titled &amp;quot;Let your Brain talk to Computers.&amp;quot;  While not Python-centric, it was very inspirational and detailed on how far science has come with respect to helping those like Stephen Hawking in the &amp;#39;locked-in&amp;#39; state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, it wouldn&amp;#39;t be a Python conference without a state of the PyPy endeavor and a GIL-less future by &lt;a href=&#34;https://ep2012.europython.eu/conference/p/armin-rigo&#34; title=&#34;Armin Rigo&#34;&gt;Armin Rigo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ep2012.europython.eu/conference/p/antonio-cuni&#34; title=&#34;Antonio Cuni&#34;&gt;Antonio Cuni&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ep2012.europython.eu/conference/p/maciej-fijalkowski&#34; title=&#34;Maciej Fijalkowski&#34;&gt;Maciej Fijalkowski&lt;/a&gt;.  I really enjoyed this talk mostly because these gentlemen had such a dorky, academic/scientist-like passion about the progression of PyPy.  Their story came off as very inspiring, honest, and enthusiastic about the massive undertaking of a project.  It was interesting that Armin even spent some time making his own Python interpreter (seriously, how passionate &amp;amp; dedicated is he?).  It will be great to see how these gentlemen progress with Transactional Memory &amp;amp; Automatic Mutual Exclusion.  Fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unexpected highlight of the evening was the quality of some lightning talks.  Specifically, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/#!/llanga&#34; title=&#34;Lukasz Langa&#34;&gt;Lukasz Langa&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/lukaszlanga/i-regret-nothing&#34; title=&#34;I Regret Nothing&#34;&gt;I Regret Nothing, You can&amp;#39;t judge me&lt;/a&gt;.  Full of hilarious memes, fast-paced jokes, and honest confession of his horrible habits, Mr Llanga showed EuroPython just how lazy of a Python programmer he is.  From simplified and nearly unidentifiable variables, to multiple inheritance, to horrific monkey patching, he convinced the audience that a) he&amp;#39;s lazy, b) he doesn&amp;#39;t regret it and c) god bless your soul if you inherit his code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To wrap up the evening, Guido van Rossum did a casual but well attended moderated Q&amp;amp;A.  He was quite frank in answering his questions, from &amp;quot;I just don&amp;#39;t know what this person is asking&amp;quot; to &amp;quot;I&amp;#39;m not going to waste my time answering this.&amp;quot;  My next post will be the loosely transcribed conversation, after I refactor it a bit to actually be readable.  But believe me when I say that while Guido is quite tired of the same question, &amp;quot;Looking back, what would you do differently&amp;quot;, he&amp;#39;s a fantastic sport that offers great dialogue for us in the Python community.  So stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">My un-talk at DjangoCon. Warning: rant.</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/my-un-talk-at-djangocon/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/my-un-talk-at-djangocon/</id>
            <updated>2012-06-06T23:45:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I woke up the morning of &lt;a href=&#34;http://2012.djangocon.eu/schedule/involving-women-in-the-community/&#34; title=&#34;DjangoCon EU Talk&#34;&gt;my talk&lt;/a&gt; lightly hung over after the awesome Divio after party for DjangoCon Europe/Zurich wanting to completely scrap my whole prepared talk this afternoon about what I&amp;#39;ve done to educate women, and how to make the &lt;a href=&#34;http://prezi.com/kzr7laiqlc-9/revenge-of-the-n00bs/?auth_key=721e5863405e7286309384eda327c2acb0616d42&#34; title=&#34;Prezi&#34;&gt;Django tutorial better&lt;/a&gt; for new folks coming into programming in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not because I&amp;#39;m hung over, or a wimp, or that I didn&amp;#39;t prepare (which I half-ass did, enough to feel fine going up on stage).  But because something else needs to be talked&lt;br&gt;
about. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women.  Women in tech.  Women at conferences. I want to make a few points about my experience here at DjangoCon: I woke up this morning a little offended.  There are about 250 attendees, about 8-10 of them are women (or at least selected female cut shirts), a ratio that is not unfamiliar, but quite low nonetheless.  Those who reviewed the talk proposals for DjangoCon Europe selected 2 women (myself included) to give a talk, and invited 2 women to serve as keynote speakers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m bothered not because of one particular thing happened.  I&amp;#39;m peeved because of many little things that added up that are independently too little of an annoyance to address. For instance, I walked into the first day of the conference; as soon as it was my turn to check in, it was assumed that I was the only female name badge that was visible on the table.  No big deal; there&amp;#39;s a high probability here that it would be me.  I don&amp;#39;t blame them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I passively mentioned a couple of times that I&amp;#39;m giving a talk at the conference, people assumed I&amp;#39;m one of the two female keynotes for the same reason, high probability that a female speaking is one of the keynotes. I&amp;#39;ll be honest: it perturbs me a little that people approach me asking how to get women involved, maybe having their female counterparts in mind, wives, girlfriends, friends, daughters, etc.  In my opinion, if that question is asked, it&amp;#39;s compounding the issue.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What should happen is not conversations about &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to get a minority in an industry to reflect population distribution in a nation. On twitter, a friend from PyCon asked me and two other folks that are here at this conference whether he should use iPython and bpython.  That was a personal win for me: it was pretty much the first time someone in the Python community solicited me for technical advice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I passively get women involved by actively pursuing what I&amp;#39;m interested in: learning how to code.  I host workshops &amp;amp; events for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pyladiessf&#34; title=&#34;PyLadies Meetup&#34;&gt;PyLadies&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/women-who-code-sf&#34; title=&#34;Women Who Code meetup&#34;&gt;Women Who Code&lt;/a&gt;, bring women down to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/2012-03-22-o-hai-there&#34; title=&#34;O HAI THERE!&#34;&gt;developers&amp;#39; conferences&lt;/a&gt; and local meetups with me, invite &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Women-Who-Code-SF/events/54634072/&#34; title=&#34;Speaker Event&#34;&gt;female speakers&lt;/a&gt; for events, meet with friends individually to tutor in Python, lots of fun things.  This indirectly creates an environment full of support and excitement, and it feels awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;#39;m telling you here: let&amp;#39;s get women involved by engaging them directly. It takes action, understanding, and doing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Gold Nuggets: My Bookmarks Collection</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/gold-nuggets-my-bookmarks-collection/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/gold-nuggets-my-bookmarks-collection/</id>
            <updated>2012-05-20T23:45:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve collected many bookmarks related to Python, programming, computer science, etc.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s time I cleaned it out and organized it better.  In the midst of doing this, I found some really awesome sites, libraries, tutorials, etc that need to be shared.  I still have plenty of bookmarks that are great resources, but I didn&amp;#39;t want to inondate readers :). I&amp;#39;ve loosely divided them up by experience level.  Here goes: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;beginner&#34;&gt;Beginner:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://sigpwned.com/content/learning-how-program&#34; title=&#34;Learning How to Program&#34;&gt;Advice&lt;/a&gt; on learning how to program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Model, View, Controller &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tomdalling.com/blog/software-design/model-view-controller-explained&#34; title=&#34;MVC Explained&#34;&gt;explained&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Basic Python Syntax &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tutorialspoint.com/python/python_basic_syntax.htm&#34; title=&#34;Basic Python Syntax&#34;&gt;Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;. (Helpful for both new toprogramming in general, and new to Python with prior programming experience).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Colorful Git &lt;a href=&#34;http://rogerdudler.github.com/git-guide/&#34; title=&#34;Git Guide&#34;&gt;Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Git Tutorial based on &lt;a href=&#34;http://openhatch.org/missions/git&#34; title=&#34;Git Missions&#34;&gt;missions to complete&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;advanced-beginnerintermediate&#34;&gt;Advanced Beginner/Intermediate:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Git &lt;a href=&#34;http://sitaramc.github.com/gcs/index.html&#34; title=&#34;Git for Scientists&#34;&gt;Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;for Scientists (although, you don&amp;#39;t need to be ascientist to get the benefit of this tutorial).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Bash Shell &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/397277/bash_shell_cheat_sheetV2.pdf&#34; title=&#34;Bash Cheat Sheet&#34;&gt;Cheat Sheet&lt;/a&gt; (Linux/Mac).  I&amp;#39;m in love with Bash.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Django tutorial:&lt;a href=&#34;http://lightbird.net/dbe/blog.html&#34; title=&#34;Django Simple Blog&#34;&gt;A simple Blog&lt;/a&gt; (uses an old version of Django).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://bpython-interpreter.org/about/&#34; title=&#34;bpython Interpreter&#34;&gt;bpython&lt;/a&gt;: an overlay to the Python interpreter.  Features in-linesyntax highlighting, autocomplete suggestions, displays a list of parameters when calling a function, displays what&amp;#39;s inside of the libraries when you import.  This is a lightweight IDE for the terminal/Python shell.  Awesome!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;experience-agnostic&#34;&gt;Experience Agnostic:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Awesome little &lt;a href=&#34;%20http://pypi.python.org/pypi/pep8&#34; title=&#34;PEP-8 tool&#34;&gt;Python library&lt;/a&gt;: checks to see if your Python file is PEP-8 compliant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://jeetworks.org/gitcommandswidget&#34; title=&#34;Git Widget&#34;&gt;Git Widget/Cheat sheet&lt;/a&gt; for Mac (lives on your dashboard for easy access).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quora.com/Python-programming-language-1/Which-Internet-companies-use-Python&#34; title=&#34;Python Companies&#34;&gt;List&lt;/a&gt;of internet companies that use Python.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">PyLadies First Workshop: Build your own Blog</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/pyladies-first-workshop-build-your-own-blog/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/pyladies-first-workshop-build-your-own-blog/</id>
            <updated>2012-05-16T23:45:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What a blast I had on Saturday! It was a great learning experience for both the attendees and for us PyLadies org board!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good lessons learned, such as virtualenv is a beast to install depending on one&amp;#39;s operating system.  Next time, we&amp;#39;ll have a pre-workshop session for installation of dependencies and such. We went through how to build a blog using Django and its class-based views.  We also went over Model-View-Controller concepts, and how they apply to Django.  We wrapped up with a quick overview of how easy it is to deploy an application on Heroku (way too easy!). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve made a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/econchick/PyLadiesBYOBlog&#34; title=&#34;PyLadies Build your own Blog&#34;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt; for people to fork &amp;amp; contribute. I didn&amp;#39;t find an easily accessible tutorial for building a blog, or for building a simple app using Django&amp;#39;s class views, so hopefully this will grow to something useful in the Django community. Til next time!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Update: PyLadiesSF Debut</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/update-pyladiessf-debut/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/update-pyladiessf-debut/</id>
            <updated>2012-04-30T17:43:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Wow, what an event it was! I&amp;#39;d say we had about ~50 attendees for our &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pyladiessf&#34; title=&#34;Event Page&#34;&gt;first event&lt;/a&gt;, which is awesome.  There was so much excitement in the room that I couldn&amp;#39;t even get a chance to hack on my projects!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://klout.com&#34; title=&#34;Klout&#34;&gt;Klout&lt;/a&gt; had a great space for us, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://linkedin.com&#34; title=&#34;LinkedIn&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; provided [too much] food. And a huge thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.robynnavarro.net/&#34; title=&#34;Robyn Navarro&#34;&gt;Robyn Navarro&lt;/a&gt; for taking time out of her schedule to come take some &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/PyLadiesSF/photos/7810542/#&#34; title=&#34;Event Pictures&#34;&gt;awesome pictures&lt;/a&gt;of the event! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve seen some very positive reviews on the meetup site, and I hope this group continues to grow with such energy.  Many women really appreciated the space and time to either learn Python or to hack on projects with new friends.  I even had the pleasure of meeting folks from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.udacity.com&#34; title=&#34;Udacity&#34;&gt;Udacity&lt;/a&gt; team; I think it&amp;#39;s such a great thing they&amp;#39;re doing: free online classes, specifically CS classes taught with Python.  We scored some free t-shirts too! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/2012_04_newbie_corner.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Newbie Corner&#34; title=&#34;Newbie Corner&#34;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was about 2/3-ish women with their +1&amp;#39;s. I was really surprised how a few folks stepped up and helped out folks learning Python and Django. For one of the newbie corners, we worked through Learn Python the Hard Way, where people earned stickers for each exercise they completed (cute, huh?). Same theme with learning Django. Who doesn&amp;#39;t like earning gold stars?! PyLadiesSF is hoping to host an event or two in May, including an intro to Python &amp;amp; Django workshop, and perhaps a Speaker Series. Stay tuned! &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Debut of PyLadiesSF</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/debut-of-pyladiessf/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/debut-of-pyladiessf/</id>
            <updated>2012-04-25T17:43:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;h4 id=&#34;before-you-read-on&#34;&gt;Before you read on: &lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have our first event this &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/PyLadiesSF/events/59189602/&#34; title=&#34;Debut Event&#34;&gt;Saturday, April 28th&lt;/a&gt; from 3p-8pm at &lt;a href=&#34;http://klout.com/home&#34; title=&#34;Klout&#34;&gt;Klout&lt;/a&gt; with an awesome dinner provided by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linkedin.com&#34; title=&#34;LinkedIn&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.  EXCITING!!! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am proud to present the founding of PyLadiesSF, the San Francisco/Bay Area chapter of &lt;a href=&#34;http://pyladies.com&#34; title=&#34;PyLadies&#34;&gt;PyLadies&lt;/a&gt;, a global mentorship group for women in the Python community.  Our mission is to promote, educate, and advance women in the field of engineering who love (or loathe…) Python. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will have monthly events, ranging from all group hack nights to various experience level bootcamps to weekly study groups. We have folks who want to learn programming, who use Python as a hobby, or develop in Python.  Ladies coming from a different language, a scientific &amp;amp; academic background, or making a career transition. It&amp;#39;s so fantastic to see these women so excited about learning and about making PyLadiesSF and every PyLady succeed.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve had many folks, women and men, approach me asking how they can help out. What surprises me the most is someone hasn&amp;#39;t done this before; why no SF chapter until now?  We&amp;#39;re Silicon Valley! But I am so excited to be a part of this, to bring the Python community together in a big wave of support for women.  I found that folks in the Python community, in the CS/engineering community as a whole, recognizes that there is an imbalance of gender.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is partly a great thing because it is very easy to find resources to help women learn and grow.  But it&amp;#39;s also unfortunate because no one puts an active effort towards advancing women. The ladies I&amp;#39;ve met and worked with are extremely enthusiastic about learning.  It&amp;#39;s certainly difficult to pursue such an endeavor; coding is hard!  But it&amp;#39;s a lot easier to ask those &amp;quot;stupid&amp;quot;, naive questions in a non-competitive environment.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kaitlyn Trigger of Lovestagram had a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/katydint84/the-story-of-lovestagram&#34; title=&#34;Kaitlyn Trigger Lovestagram Slides&#34;&gt;great metaphor for programming&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/building_furniture.png&#34; alt=&#34;Furniture&#34; title=&#34;Directions for Building Furniture&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How in the h&amp;amp;ll do you get from step 1 to step 2?  Either a magic wand, or you are a carpenter by nature.  Similar with engineering: talk to development folks, ask for a product and it magically appears all constructed.  I had a hard time grasping how a for loop, classes, and methods can turn into an architecture for a cloud fileshare system, or a social networking site, or even a simple greedy change calculator. I found that having someone that also comes from this &amp;quot;what is this wizardry?!&amp;quot; point of view helps break down the steps to actually create a meaningful program. Enter: ME! I invite anyone who has an interest in Python to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pyladiessf&#34; title=&#34;PyLadiesSF Meetup&#34;&gt;come check us out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">O HAI THERE!</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/o-hai-there/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/o-hai-there/</id>
            <updated>2012-03-22T23:49:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Who knew I&amp;#39;d get wrapped into Silicon Valley?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should post more so I don&amp;#39;t have to do such a digest of what&amp;#39;s been going on! :) It all started when I took my first CS class. Well, it sucked. Learning first in C, I thought, “Well, I know some of these words.” I [re]assure you, C does not come naturally to a (former) financial analyst.  I felt&lt;br&gt;
I was drowning: I failed both exams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of attending Science Hack Day, where I was first exposed to Python.  Then it was all downhill from there... My final project was &lt;a href=&#34;http://inflatr.com&#34; title=&#34;InflatR&#34;&gt;inflatr.com&lt;/a&gt;, which used the awesomeness of Python and my undying interest in economics.  Python is actually an interesting language; it poses as an easy-to-learn language for beginner coders, but it more so leverages the coder to build programs and scripts efficiently by taking away a lot of the tediousness that other languages are known for and where beginners drown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then had the audacity to start up a study group for women wanting to learn Python.  Standing on the shoulders of the newly founded &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/women-who-code-sf&#34; title=&#34;Women Who Code meetup&#34;&gt;Women Who Code&lt;/a&gt; group (growing at a linear rate of 100 members a month without skipping a beat!).  Never had I organized a group like this before, but let me tell you: it was so easy, it begged to be done.  Within a few days of conceiving of the idea, I had gotten the &amp;#39;okay&amp;#39; from Women Who Code, found space at Dropbox who generously agreed to hosting the group for 8 weeks &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; join them for dinner every meetup, and secured Guido van Rossum, the Benevolent Dictator of Life at Google, aka the founder and creator of Python, to kick off the first event. The first meetup guest list filled up within hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time the study series got into its grove, I received sponsorship from PyLadies to attend the mecca of all Python users - PyCon, down in Santa Clara.  On top of that, I received a grant that included two free PyCon registrations (normally ~$300) as well as $100 off registration, and $300 to rent a car to bring these women from the SF area to PyCon.  Lastly, I scored a FOSS Sponsorship booth that allowed Women Who Code to represent and promote the group at the conversation.  Seeing as how we didn&amp;#39;t have any of the typical &amp;#39;marketing materials&amp;#39; that one would need at a conference, I asked for and instantly received another grant for $200 to get a banner, a poster, some stickers and 5000 business cards all with Women Who Code&amp;#39;s name and mission. It was one of the best experiences ever, both attending PyCon and working with the women that attended my study group.  My name and actions within this community are known before I arrive anywhere now.  There is so much energy and crave to learn Python in a safe environment that I just can&amp;#39;t stop now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PyLadies approached me a couple months ago to start a San Francisco chapter, and now I&amp;#39;m going full force! So now my current projects are to get PyLadies SF going, to clean up and implement new applications to my inflation site, to continue coding in Python and increase my algorithms education, and to continue being awesome. :-) Stay tuned: this weekend I&amp;#39;ll produce a postmortem on my recently passed laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">It&#39;s for SCIENCE</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/its-for-science/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/its-for-science/</id>
            <updated>2011-11-14T23:44:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Guten tag, all. I just had an awesome weekend.  I attended &lt;a href=&#34;http://sciencehackday.pbworks.com/w/page/45740104/SFideas&#34; title=&#34;SF Science Hack Day&#34;&gt;San Francisco Science Hack Day&lt;/a&gt; and it was &lt;em&gt;awesome&lt;/em&gt;!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was two &lt;strong&gt;full days&lt;/strong&gt;, so let me lay it out for you: &lt;strong&gt;about me:&lt;/strong&gt;programming &amp;amp; science n00b &lt;strong&gt;mission:&lt;/strong&gt;to make &amp;amp; hack things with SCIENCE &lt;strong&gt;vision:&lt;/strong&gt;to hack data from Switzerland&amp;#39;s Large Hadron Collider for better accessibility and understanding, esp for enthusiasts but n00bs like me. &lt;strong&gt;results:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  my knowledge of particle physics went from 0 to ... some? probably 1
if it&amp;#39;s on a scale of ...100.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  crash course in python and javascript programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  +5lbs from bountiful free food and alcohol&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Increased tolerance to caffeine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  I made &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mattbellis.com/index.php?title=LHC_Hack_Day/Mass_distributions&#34; title=&#34;Mass Distributions Viz&#34;&gt;THIS&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  The group collectively put &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mattbellis.com/index.php?title=LHC_Data_Hack&#34; title=&#34;LHC Data Hack&#34;&gt;THIS&lt;/a&gt; website together!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  10 GBs of LHC data, out of the gazillion terabytes of data both available &amp;amp; unavailable to the &amp;quot;public&amp;quot; (I say with quotes because not exactly sure where I could even get the publicly released data...)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: If you&amp;#39;re interested in the source code, it can be found on GitHub under mattbellis. So, what those two graphs mean that I put together is [I THINK, IF I REMEMBER CORRECTLY] a reflection of two different ways to calculate mass of muons. Muons produce when two protons collide together, along with other particles, including mesons. The second graph (using Einstein&amp;#39;s equations/special relativity), you can see a second &amp;quot;hump&amp;quot;, signaling that there actually is a second meson existing that the first graph didn&amp;#39;t show. All &amp;#39;n all, thanks to my intro course to computer science, I was able to have somewhat of an understanding of what was going on, as well as built upon my skills (especially for my final project coming up!).   All I have to say for those n00bs to any new skill: Dive right in.  That&amp;#39;s the best, most fun way to learn! &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Studying BitCoin</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/studying-bitcoin/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/studying-bitcoin/</id>
            <updated>2011-07-07T23:44:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Has anyone else heard of BitCoin, and the incredible inflation it has seen? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;http://falkvinge.net/2011/05/29/why-im-putting-all-my-savings-into-bitcoin/&#34; title=&#34;Why I&amp;#39;m Putting All my Savings into Bitcoin&#34;&gt;dude&lt;/a&gt; has put &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt;his money into BitCoin - not smart, I would say.  Especially when &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailytech.com/article.aspx?newsid=21877&#34; title=&#34;Run on Bitcoin&#34;&gt;news&lt;/a&gt; like a run on BitCoin hits. (If you have no clue on what BitCoin is, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bitcoin&#34; title=&#34;Wiki: Bitcoin&#34;&gt;read&lt;/a&gt;.) So while I laugh at the guy who invested all his money that is now gone, I reflect back on a conversation I had with a friend a few years ago.  Can we use this virtual currency to study monetary economics?  BitCoin has the potential to provide us with an interesting avenue to understand another type of currency. But what I am imagining more is looking at virtual worlds and video games (disclaimer: I have no direct experience with video games) to build scenarios to &amp;quot;test&amp;quot; on live people interacting with the world/game.  Currently, there are trading simulators that follow the market where one can see how his/her virtual portfolio would fair in real life.  Add that aspect to a virtual economy and see how quantitative easing programs could affect it. Just an idea.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title type="html">Seattle Tech Talk</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.roguelynn.com/words/seattle-tech-talk/" type="text/html" />
            <id>http://www.roguelynn.com/words/seattle-tech-talk/</id>
            <updated>2011-06-30T17:43:00Z</updated>

            <author>
                <name>Lynn Root</name>
                <email>lynn@lynnroot.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.roguelynn.com/</uri>
            </author>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had the interesting experience of attending a Seattle tech talk with Facebook&amp;#39;s Mark Zuckerberg. Unfortunately I was too scared to ask him if he felt $70 billion was a fair value for the FB IPO estimate, or if he needed any analysts to help him justify such a number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what I though was interesting that he said, beyond all that geeky coding and infrastructure talk, was that he believes the rate of people &amp;quot;sharing&amp;quot; stuff via Facebook will double each year, so within 5 years people will be sharing 32x as many things compared to today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is that even possible? ~1024 things/day being shared/liked/commented. We&amp;#39;d have to be FBing nearly every minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I think is more accurate is an exponential growth of a person sharing, then as one gets older, the activity tapers, slows down, and maybe even fall to zero/very rare. What would be important would be to look at that age where exponential growth happens and see how that is growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just quick thoughts post-talk. I enjoyed it, plus the free pizza &amp;amp; booze. Although I wish I could have gotten some free swag...  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.roguelynn.com/assets/images/mark_zuckerberg.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;the Zuck&#34; title=&#34;Mark Zuckerberg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
        
    
</feed>